<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37688"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-29T12:20:57"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-16T10:53:16"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Meden, Katja</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37688" GROUPID="37688">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">The Contribution of Male and Female Teachers to the Foundation of Empirical Pedagogy in Serbia, with Reference to Serbian Association for Child Psychology</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="srp">Doprinos učitelja i učiteljica zasnivanju empirijske pedagogije u Srbiji, na primeru Srpskog društva za dečju psihologiju</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Stankov, Ljiljana</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The Association of Serbian Teachers was founded in 1881. It launched its own journal The Teacher, at the very beginning of the next year. In the last decade of the 19th century this Association founded also the School Museum. In the first decade of the last century the branches of the Association published their own local journals. During that time, the idea that teachers can contribute to the foundation and development of national pedagogy, based on the research of physical and psychical development of Serbian children, matured. At the initiative of the 16th generation of graduated students of the Male Teacher Training College, the Serbian Association for Child Psychology was founded in Belgrade in 1907. The Association assembled more than 500 members, who were mostly teachers and professors. They published their own journal - The Herald. The Association organized three meetings, one course from the field of child psychology, 22 surveys. The surveys were conducted with the aim to study different issues of child development, like anthropometric measurements, children’s speech, drawings, basic concepts like numbers, children’s ideals, as well as their learning styles, memory and reckoning. The exhibition with photographs, audio track, written materials and craftworks of children up to 15 was prepared, with the view to collect material for the foundation of the psychology of Serbian children. They also had ambition to offer teachers a professional training in the field of child psychology. Due to persistence of teachers from the district of Vranje, a small laboratory was open there, with the most modern equipment ordered from the Zimmerman’s factory in Leipzig, although that district was one of the poorest in the country. After 1910 the Association stopped its activities due to lack of money for professional seminars and lectures and for publishing the journal, since the state authorities did not offer adequate support.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="srp">Srpsko učiteljsko društvo je osnovano 1881. godine. Već početkom naredne godine je pokrenulo svoj časopis – Učitelj. U poslednjoj deceniji XIX veka osnovalo je i Školski muzej. U prvoj deceniji prošlog veka i okružni ogranci udruženja pokreću svoje časopise. U ovom periodu je sazrela ideja da učitelji mogu da doprinesu osnivanju i razvoju nacionalne pedagogije, koja je zasnovana na istraživanjima fizičkog i psihičkog razvoja srpske dece. Na inicijativu 16. kola svršenih đaka Muške učiteljske škole, u Beogradu je 1907. godine osnovano Srpsko društvo za dečju psihologiju. Društvo je okupilo više od 500 članova, uglavnom učitelja i profesora. Pokrenuli su svoj časopis – Glasnik. Društvo je organizovalo tri skupa, jedan kurs iz oblasti dečje psihologije i pokrenulo 22 ankete (istraživanja). Ova istraživanja su pokrenuta sa ciljem da se proučavaju različite oblasti dečjeg razvoja, kao što su: antropometrijska merenja, razvoj govora, dečji crteži, formiranje pojmova o brojevima, dečji ideali, stilovi učenja, pamćenje, računske radnje. Pripremana je izložba koja je imala za cilj da putem fotografija, tonskih zapisa, pisanih i ručnih radova dece, uzrasta do 15 godina, pruži materijal za zasnivanje psihologije srpskog deteta. Takođe su nastojali da omoguće učiteljima profesionalno usavršavanje u oblasti dečje psihologije. Zahvaljujući upornosti učitelja iz vranjskog okruga, u Vranju je otvorena mala laboratorija sa modernom opremom nabavljenom iz Cimermanove fabrike u Lajpcigu, iako je taj okrug bio jedan od najsiromašnijih u zemlji. Posle 1910. godine Društvo je prestalo da deluje, prvenstveno zbog nedostatka materijalnih sredstava za organizovanje stručnih seminara i predavanja kao i za objavljivanje svog časopisa, pošto nije imalo dovoljnu podršku državnih prosvetnih vlasti.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Delphine Campagolle (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-27</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37688">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37688</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37688</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37688">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The Association of Serbian Teachers was founded in 1881. It
                                        launched its own journal The Teacher, at the very beginning
                                        of the next year. In the last decade of the 19th century
                                        this Association founded also the School Museum. In the
                                        first decade of the last century the branches of the
                                        Association published their own local journals. During that
                                        time, the idea that teachers can contribute to the
                                        foundation and development of national pedagogy, based on
                                        the research of physical and psychical development of
                                        Serbian children, matured. At the initiative of the 16th
                                        generation of graduated students of the Male Teacher
                                        Training College, the Serbian Association for Child
                                        Psychology was founded in Belgrade in 1907. The Association
                                        assembled more than 500 members, who were mostly teachers
                                        and professors. They published their own journal - The
                                        Herald. The Association organized three meetings, one course
                                        from the field of child psychology, 22 surveys. The surveys
                                        were conducted with the aim to study different issues of
                                        child development, like anthropometric measurements,
                                        children’s speech, drawings, basic concepts like numbers,
                                        children’s ideals, as well as their learning styles, memory
                                        and reckoning. The exhibition with photographs, audio track,
                                        written materials and craftworks of children up to 15 was
                                        prepared, with the view to collect material for the
                                        foundation of the psychology of Serbian children. They also
                                        had ambition to offer teachers a professional training in
                                        the field of child psychology. Due to persistence of
                                        teachers from the district of Vranje, a small laboratory was
                                        open there, with the most modern equipment ordered from the
                                        Zimmerman’s factory in Leipzig, although that district was
                                        one of the poorest in the country. After 1910 the
                                        Association stopped its activities due to lack of money for
                                        professional seminars and lectures and for publishing the
                                        journal, since the state authorities did not offer adequate
                                        support.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/H2egpKFJYYE"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37686"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37688" ADMID="premis.37688 entity.37688">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
