<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37440"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-04-05T08:58:49"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-04-07T11:32:29"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.4" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Mirc</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37440" GROUPID="37440">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">How Do Out-Of-Area Teachers in German Secondary Schools Deal with the French Revolution and with National Socialism?</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:creator>Götz, Georg</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">German teacher education traditionally centers on the provision of domain-specific content knowledge and pedagogical content knowledge at the expense of plain pedagogical knowledge. At the same time however, a lot of classes in secondary schools are taught by teachers who did not study the subject of these classes. The German educational sector keeps living with this obvious contradiction because this type of out-of-area teaching primarily takes place in school types of Germany’s segregated system that traditionally attract little attention from the academic discourse. How do out-of-area teachers cope with this paradox task? I have conducted interviews with both teachers with and without a degree in history. For these interviews, I asked them to bring along material they ‘successfully’ applied in class. I asked for a piece of material on the French Revolution and one on a topic of their choice. In explaining their materials, the teachers provided insight into their system of beliefs pertaining to history and to the teaching of history. Preliminary results show that both out-of-area teachers and in-area teachers conceive the French Revolution along remarkably similar lines often presenting similar material for similar learning routines. Obviously both the curriculum and available textbooks help to level the influence of different domain traditions. At the same time, the significance of interaction among teachers in their respective schools should not be overlooked. All this helps to make for a remarkably similar concept of history and history teaching.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">qualitative research</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">interviews</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">secondary schools</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">Germany</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">teacher beliefs</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">kvalitativna raziskava</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">intervjuji</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">srednje šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">Nemčija</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Josué Llull Peñalba (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2016-09-29</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37440">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37440</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37440</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37440">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng"> German teacher education
                                    traditionally centers on the provision of domain-specific
                                    content knowledge and pedagogical content knowledge at the
                                    expense of plain pedagogical knowledge. At the same time
                                    however, a lot of classes in secondary schools are taught by
                                    teachers who did not study the subject of these classes. The
                                    German educational sector keeps living with this obvious
                                    contradiction because this type of out-of-area teaching
                                    primarily takes place in school types of Germany’s segregated
                                    system that traditionally attract little attention from the
                                    academic discourse. How do out-of-area teachers cope with this
                                    paradox task? I have conducted interviews with both teachers
                                    with and without a degree in history. For these interviews, I
                                    asked them to bring along material they ‘successfully’ applied
                                    in class. I asked for a piece of material on the French
                                    Revolution and one on a topic of their choice. In explaining
                                    their materials, the teachers provided insight into their system
                                    of beliefs pertaining to history and to the teaching of history.
                                    Preliminary results show that both out-of-area teachers and
                                    in-area teachers conceive the French Revolution along remarkably
                                    similar lines often presenting similar material for similar
                                    learning routines. Obviously both the curriculum and available
                                    textbooks help to level the influence of different domain
                                    traditions. At the same time, the significance of interaction
                                    among teachers in their respective schools should not be
                                    overlooked. All this helps to make for a remarkably similar
                                    concept of history and history teaching. </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/s9R8EAoAKbM"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37387"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37440" ADMID="premis.37440 entity.37440">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
