<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37736"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-06-12T11:34:58"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-12T11:46:00"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37736" GROUPID="37736">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Opening ceremony</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">Greetings of representatives of supporters and organisations: Ministry of Education, Science and Sport (Aljuš Pertinač) Secondary School of Nursing Ljubljana (Marija Verbič) Slovenian School Museum (Stane Okoliš) Historical association of Slovenia &amp; Symposium 2013 Committee (Branko Šuštar) ICOM – Slovenia (Irena Marušič) Branko Šuštar: Welcome to the 15th Symposium: How do school museums and our Symposiums forge links among us? Tjaša Šuštar (in Spanish), Maja Hakl (in German) Welcome to the 15th Symposium 'Creating links in education': How do school/education museums and our Symposiums forge links among us? Forging links (or creating links as the title of Symposium is formed) is one of the fundamental missions of museums that report past stories for present times so that previous experience and wisdom can build tomorrow in a united Europe and a connected world. Our school and education museums unite the history of education – as a story of the forms, methods and the content used inconveying culture – with today’s school and with lessons for the future. School museums strive no lessardently for international links, which have been established since 1984 through biannual meetings.Thus we learn from each other, seek encouragement, hear about differences and discover shared characteristics and connections with educational endeavours throughout history. This year’s theme unites teachers in teachers’ associations with their school and pedagogic activities: in the shape of trade union striving, professional teacher training, the educational press and textbooks, and international meetings and connections. Knowledge is international and pedagogic ideas spread heedless of political and ideological dividing lines, and so the meetings of our museums, our scholarly gatherings and our research have for decades been transcending state borders and political connections. For 30 years school museum symposium have been connecting the representatives of a big, but very diverse family of school, pedagogic, education and school museums and collections. Recently, we have begun calling our meetings International Symposia on School Life and School History Museums &amp; Collections. These are attended by national, regional, town and other museums and collections relating to education from nearly 30 European countries as well as from other continents. Each and every symposium is also a precious link between the museum world and the world of science, research and the university, whilst the symposia also serve as an opportunity for contact between colleagues in the diverse field of the history of education. Thus this year’s 15th symposium (for celebration of 115 years of est. of Slovenian School Museum), which is for the first time taking place in a Slavic country, unites 90 participants and offers 60 talks on school/pedagogic museums and on the role of school associations in the history of education. Between English and various mother tongues. Initially, German was spoken at our symposium and we could almost say that it was their mother tongue, since the idea for these gatherings came in 1984 from Rudolf Lukschanderl (1927-1990), who invited school museums to Michelstetten in Austria, thus instigating biannual museum gatherings: Internationales Symposium der Schulmuseen und Schulgeschichtlichen Sammlungen. Later, the symposium became bi- or tri-lingual, depending on financial resources for interpreting) – English was adopted as a modern ‘lingua franca’. In spite of this, our 15th symposium in the centre of Ljubljana, the capital of the Slovenians, who have partly forged their national identity through the establishment of Slovenian as the mother tongue in education, must respectfully address the importance of all our mother tongues. We could paraphrase the Bible and say ‘let every language celebrate God’, or put it poetically: ‘let the voice of every bird be heard’. This is why the summaries of our contributions can be read in Symposium Book not only in English, as the language of international communication and the symposium’s working language, but also in the mother tongue of each individual speaker. A part of the symposium also takes the form the location and country, with simultaneous translation, but often – for practical reasons and lack of of what we have called the “Babel section” and is held in various languages from three language groups. Symposium webpage.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Muzealije (glasbena skupina)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:contributor>Tjaša Šuštar (španščina)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:contributor>Maja Hakl (nemščina)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-26</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">Event</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">spa</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">deu</dcterms:language>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37736">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37736</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37736</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37736">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="slv">
                  <a xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
                     href="http://www.ssolski-muzej.si/slo/symposium2013.php">Spletna stran simpozija/Slovenski šolski muzej.</a>
               </entity:description>
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">Greetings of representatives of supporters and organisations:
                                        Ministry of Education, Science and Sport (Aljuš Pertinač)
                                        Secondary School of Nursing Ljubljana (Marija Verbič)
                                        Slovenian School Museum (Stane Okoliš) Historical
                                        association of Slovenia &amp; Symposium 2013 Committee
                                        (Branko Šuštar) ICOM – Slovenia (Irena Marušič) Branko
                                        Šuštar: Welcome to the 15th Symposium: How do school museums
                                        and our Symposiums forge links among us? Tjaša Šuštar (in
                                        Spanish), Maja Hakl (in German) Welcome to the 15th
                                        Symposium 'Creating links in education': How do
                                        school/education museums and our Symposiums forge links
                                        among us? Forging links (or creating links as the title of
                                        Symposium is formed) is one of the fundamental missions of
                                        museums that report past stories for present times so that
                                        previous experience and wisdom can build tomorrow in a
                                        united Europe and a connected world. Our school and
                                        education museums unite the history of education – as a
                                        story of the forms, methods and the content used inconveying
                                        culture – with today’s school and with lessons for the
                                        future. School museums strive no lessardently for
                                        international links, which have been established since 1984
                                        through biannual meetings.Thus we learn from each other,
                                        seek encouragement, hear about differences and discover
                                        shared characteristics and connections with educational
                                        endeavours throughout history. This year’s theme unites
                                        teachers in teachers’ associations with their school and
                                        pedagogic activities: in the shape of trade union striving,
                                        professional teacher training, the educational press and
                                        textbooks, and international meetings and connections.
                                        Knowledge is international and pedagogic ideas spread
                                        heedless of political and ideological dividing lines, and so
                                        the meetings of our museums, our scholarly gatherings and
                                        our research have for decades been transcending state
                                        borders and political connections. For 30 years school
                                        museum symposium have been connecting the representatives of
                                        a big, but very diverse family of school, pedagogic,
                                        education and school museums and collections. Recently, we
                                        have begun calling our meetings International Symposia on
                                        School Life and School History Museums &amp; Collections.
                                        These are attended by national, regional, town and other
                                        museums and collections relating to education from nearly 30
                                        European countries as well as from other continents. Each
                                        and every symposium is also a precious link between the
                                        museum world and the world of science, research and the
                                        university, whilst the symposia also serve as an opportunity
                                        for contact between colleagues in the diverse field of the
                                        history of education. Thus this year’s 15th symposium (for
                                        celebration of 115 years of est. of Slovenian School
                                        Museum), which is for the first time taking place in a
                                        Slavic country, unites 90 participants and offers 60 talks
                                        on school/pedagogic museums and on the role of school
                                        associations in the history of education. Between English
                                        and various mother tongues. Initially, German was spoken at
                                        our symposium and we could almost say that it was their
                                        mother tongue, since the idea for these gatherings came in
                                        1984 from Rudolf Lukschanderl (1927-1990), who invited
                                        school museums to Michelstetten in Austria, thus instigating
                                        biannual museum gatherings: Internationales Symposium der
                                        Schulmuseen und Schulgeschichtlichen Sammlungen. Later, the
                                        symposium became bi- or tri-lingual, depending on financial
                                        resources for interpreting) – English was adopted as a
                                        modern ‘lingua franca’. In spite of this, our 15th symposium
                                        in the centre of Ljubljana, the capital of the Slovenians,
                                        who have partly forged their national identity through the
                                        establishment of Slovenian as the mother tongue in
                                        education, must respectfully address the importance of all
                                        our mother tongues. We could paraphrase the Bible and say
                                        ‘let every language celebrate God’, or put it poetically:
                                        ‘let the voice of every bird be heard’. This is why the
                                        summaries of our contributions can be read in Symposium Book
                                        not only in English, as the language of international
                                        communication and the symposium’s working language, but also
                                        in the mother tongue of each individual speaker. A part of
                                        the symposium also takes the form the location and country,
                                        with simultaneous translation, but often – for practical
                                        reasons and lack of of what we have called the “Babel
                                        section” and is held in various languages from three
                                        language groups. <a href="http://www.ssolski-muzej.si/slo/symposium2013.php">Symposium webpage.</a>
                  </p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/20243"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37736" ADMID="premis.37736 entity.37736">
            <METS:div TYPE="entity">
               <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37737"/>
            </METS:div>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
