<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/20497"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2014-01-10T07:17:09"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-02-07T11:42:41"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.20497" GROUPID="20497">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Bosnia and Herzegovina (1943-1993): A Short Overview</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="bos">Bosna i Hercegovina (1943.-1993.) – kratak pregled</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="slv">Bosna in Hercegovina (1943-1993): kratek pregled</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Katz, Vera</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="bos">Posljednje dvije godine Drugog svetskog rata bile su vrlo važne za Bosnui Hercegovinu jer je postojalo neslaganje u vezi s njenim statusom, odnosnodvojba vodstva Komunističke partije Jugoslavije između autonomne pokrajinei konstitutivne republike u budućoj socijalističkoj federaciji. Na Drugom zasjedanjuAVNOJ-a riješeno je pitanje statusa Bosne i Hercegovine, a tijekomcijelog socijalističkog perioda citirane su odluke i izvodi iz Deklaracije Drugogzasjedanja ZAVNOBiH-a, a datum njegovog održavanja – 25. studeni – slavljenje kao Dan državnosti BiH, koji se danas obilježava samo u dijelu FederacijeBiH s bošnjačkom većinom.U socijalističkoj Jugoslaviji Bosna i Hercegovina bila je u skupini nerazvijenihrepublika, ovisna o financijskim sredstvima Fonda za nerazvijene. Do sredinešezdesetih godina postigla je značajan napredak u svim vrstama djelatnosti.Osim toga, kao središnja republika Jugoslavije, a između Hrvatske i Srbije, bilaje zbog višenacionalnog sastava stanovništva neizostavno naglašavana kao primjeročuvanja bratstva i jedinstva jugoslavenskih naroda i narodnosti. Osimtoga, u javnom mnijenju vladalo je mišljenje da je bosanskohercegovački prostorsrce obrane od spoljne agresije na Jugoslaviju, ali i najčvršći čuvar komunističkevlasti. Dolaskom kriznih 80-ih godina, Bosnu i Hercegovinu potresalo jenekoliko gospodarskih afera i sudskih procesa, a jugoslavenski politički i gospodarskinesporazumi uglavnom su se refl ektirali u njenoj svakodnevici, gdje jevišenacionalnost predstavljala sve veći teret.Politički događaji s kraja 80-ih i početka 90-ih godina 20. stoljeća razorilisu u potpunosti bosanskohercegovačko društvo građeno tijekom socijalizma idoveli su do četvorogodišnjeg rata u kojem su se desili brojni ratni zločini, genocidi razaranje zajedničkih institucija bosanskohercegovačke vlasti i kulture.Mada je već u rujnu 1991. započela agresija na bosanskohercegovački teritorij,6. travnja 1992. na dan priznavanja neovisnosti Bosne i Hercegovine počeo jerat koji je samo za jednu godinu (1993.) prerastao u srpsko – bošnjačko – hrvatskisukob, a u dijelu Bosne i u međubošnjački. Do studenog 1995. (Daytonskisporazum) rat je odnio oko stotinu tisuća života, ostavio veliki broj invalida i raseliobrojno stanovništvo unutar Bosne i Hercegovine i izvan nje, u inozemstvo.Danas, Bosna i Hercegovina – podijeljena ili sastavljena od dva entiteta, ovisnoo tumačenju, pripada zemljama Zapadnog Balkana, novouspostavljenog nazivaza politički i gospodarski neefikasne zemlje.Iz današnje perspektive, istraživanje socijalističkog razdoblja u povijestiBosne i Hercegovine otvara mnoga pitanja, a na većinu njih nema utemeljenihodgovora u domaćoj historiografi ji. Mada od šezdesetih godina u domaćojznanstvenoj javnosti postoji ideja da se napiše povijest Bosne i Hercegovine dodanas nije ostvarena.</dcterms:abstract>
            <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="slv">Zadnji dve leti druge svetovne vojne sta bili za Bosno in Hercegovino zelopomembni zaradi nerazumevanja njenega položaja oziroma dvoma vodstva Komunističnepartije Jugoslavije glede tega, ali bo v bodoči socialistični federacijipredstavljala avtonomno pokrajino ali konstitutivno republiko. Na drugem zasedanjuAVNOJ (Antifašistično vijeće narodnog oslobođenja) je bilo vprašanjepoložaja Bosne in Hercegovine sicer formalno rešeno, a so bile v vsem socialističnemobdobju navajane predvsem odločitve in sklepi iz deklaracije drugegazasedanja ZAVNOBiH (Zemaljsko antifašističko vijeće narodnog oslobođenjaBosne i Hercegovine) 25. novembra 1943 v Mrkonjić Gradu. Ta dan je obeleževankot Dan državnosti BiH, ki pa se danes slavi samo v delih Federacije BIH,kjer živijo večinoma Bošnjaki.V socialistični Jugoslaviji je bila Bosna in Hercegovina v skupini nerazvitihrepublik in s tem odvisna od finančnih sredstev Sklada za nerazvite (Skladfederacije za kreditiranje hitrejšega razvoja gospodarsko manj razvitih republikin Kosova). Do sredine šestdesetih let je dosegla pomemben napredek v vsehdejavnostih. Poleg tega je bila kot zemljepisno osrednja jugoslovanska republikamed Hrvaško in Srbijo zaradi večnacionalne sestave prebivalstva neizbežnopoudarjena kot primer ohranjanja bratstva in enotnosti jugoslovanskih narodovin narodnosti. Prevladovalo je tudi mnenje, da bosanskohercegovski prostorpredstavlja srce obrambe pred zunanjo agresijo na Jugoslavijo in s tem najmočnejšegačuvaja komunistične oblasti. V kriznih osemdesetih letih je Bosno inHercegovino pretresalo nekaj gospodarskih afer in sodnih procesov, medtemko so jugoslovanski politični in gospodarski nesporazumi odsevali večinoma vnjenem vsakdanu, kjer je njena večnacionalnost predstavljala vse večjo težavo.Politični dogodki ob koncu osemdesetih in v začetku devetdesetih let 20.stoletja so bosanskohercegovsko družbo, kakršna se je oblikovala v socialističnemobdobju, tudi pripeljali do štiriletne vojne, v kateri so se zgodili številnivojni zločini, genocid in rušenje skupnih inštitucij bosanskohercegovskih oblastiin kulture. Čeprav se je agresija na na bosanskohercegovsko ozemlje pričelaže septembra 1991, je vojna izbruhnila 6. aprila 1992, na dan priznanjaneodvisnosti BiH. Vojna je le v enem letu (1993) prerasla v srbsko-bošnjaško27-hrvaški vojaški spopad, v delu Bosne pa celo v medbošnjaški. Do novembra1995 (Daytonski sporazum) je vojna vzela okoli sto tisoč življenj, pustila velikoštevilo invalidov in razselila številno prebivalstvo tako znotraj BiH kot tudi vinozemstvo. Danes Bosna in Hercegovina, ki je razdeljena oziroma jo sestavljatadve entiteti, odvisno od tolmačenja, spada med države Zahodnega Balkana.Ta predstavlja novonastali naziv za politično in gospodarsko neuspešne države.Iz današnje perspektive raziskovanje socialističnega obdobja v zgodoviniBosne in Hercegovine odpira številna vprašanja, vendar nanje domačem zgodovinopisjevečinoma ne ponuja odgovorov. V domači znanstveni javnosti sicerže od šestdesetih let obstaja ideja o izdelavi sintetične zgodovine Bosne in Hercegovine,vendar ta do danes še ni napisana.</dcterms:abstract>
            <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="eng">The last two years of World War II were very important for Bosnia and Herzegovina,since the Communist Party of Yugoslavia did not understand its positionor doubted whether it should become an autonomous province or constitutiverepublic in the future socialist federation. At the second session of AVNOJ(Anti-Fascist Council of National Liberation of Yugoslavia) the question ofthe position of Bosnia and Herzegovina was solved. However, throughout thesocialist period the decisions and conclusions from the second session of ZAVNOBiH(State Anti-fascist Council for the National Liberation of Bosnia andHerzegovina) were referred to, and the date of 25 November 1943 (MrkonjićGrad) is the Statehood Day of Bosnia and Herzegovina. Today, though, it isonly celebrated in the parts of the federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina whereBosniak population is in the majority.In the socialist Yugoslavia, Bosnia and Herzegovina belonged to the groupof underdeveloped republics and depended on the financial resources from theUnderdeveloped Fund (federal fund for providing loans in order to facilitatethe development of economically underdeveloped republics and Kosovo). Untilthe mid-1960s it achieved important progress in all aspects. Furthermore, as the(geographically) central Yugoslav republic, located between Croatia and Serbia,it unavoidably represented a model of preserving the brotherhood and unityof the Yugoslav nations and nationalities due to its multi-national populationstructure. The opinion that Bosnian-Herzegovinian space represented the heartof the defence from any external aggression against Yugoslavia and that it wasthe strongest guard of the communist authorities was also prominent. During the1980s crisis Bosnia and Herzegovina was shaken by a few economic affairs andjudicial processes, but everyday life there was mostly affected by the Yugoslavpolitical and economic disagreements, and its multi-nationality represented anincreasingly severe problem.The political events at the end of the 1980s and in the beginning of the 1990sinvolved the whole of Bosnian-Herzegovinian society, shaped during the socialistperiod, in a four-year war, during which numerous war crimes, genocide anddestruction of the common institutions of the Bosnian-Herzegovinian authoritiesand culture took place. Although aggression against the Bosnian-Herzegovinianterritory began already in September 1991, the war officially started on6 April 1992, on the day of the recognition of the Bosnian-Herzegovinian independence.In only one year (1993) this war developed into a military conflictbetween Serbs, Bosniaks and Croats, and in parts of Bosnia also in a conflictbetween Bosniaks. Until November 1995 (Dayton Agreement) this war claimedaround 100,000 lives, resulted in a large number of persons with disabilities,and displaced the population within Bosnia and Herzegovina as well as beyondits borders. Today Bosnia and Herzegovina, divided into two entities, belongs– depending on the interpretation – among the states of the Western Balkans,which is the newly-coined expression for politically and economically unsuccessfulcountries.From today’s perspective the exploration of the socialist period in the historyof Bosnia and Herzegovina opens many questions, but Bosnian-Herzegovinianhistoriography does not possess well-founded answers for most of them. Eventhough in the Bosnian-Herzegovinian scientific community the idea of writingthe history of Bosnia and Herzegovina has existed since the 1960s, to date thishas not been achieved.</dcterms:abstract>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">Slovenija</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">Jugoslavija</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">posvetovanja</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">1941-1991</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">Slovenia</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">Yugoslavia</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">symposium</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">1941-1991</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Muzej novejše zgodovine Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Damijan Guštin (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-11-29</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">bos</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.20497">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>20497</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/20497</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.20497">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="slv">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">Zadnji dve leti druge svetovne vojne sta bili za Bosno in
                                        Hercegovino zelopomembni zaradi nerazumevanja njenega
                                        položaja oziroma dvoma vodstva Komunističnepartije
                                        Jugoslavije glede tega, ali bo v bodoči socialistični
                                        federacijipredstavljala avtonomno pokrajino ali
                                        konstitutivno republiko. Na drugem zasedanjuAVNOJ
                                        (Antifašistično vijeće narodnog oslobođenja) je bilo
                                        vprašanjepoložaja Bosne in Hercegovine sicer formalno
                                        rešeno, a so bile v vsem socialističnemobdobju navajane
                                        predvsem odločitve in sklepi iz deklaracije drugegazasedanja
                                        ZAVNOBiH (Zemaljsko antifašističko vijeće narodnog
                                        oslobođenjaBosne i Hercegovine) 25. novembra 1943 v Mrkonjić
                                        Gradu. Ta dan je obeleževankot Dan državnosti BiH, ki pa se
                                        danes slavi samo v delih Federacije BIH,kjer živijo večinoma
                                        Bošnjaki.V socialistični Jugoslaviji je bila Bosna in
                                        Hercegovina v skupini nerazvitihrepublik in s tem odvisna od
                                        finančnih sredstev Sklada za nerazvite (Skladfederacije za
                                        kreditiranje hitrejšega razvoja gospodarsko manj razvitih
                                        republikin Kosova). Do sredine šestdesetih let je dosegla
                                        pomemben napredek v vsehdejavnostih. Poleg tega je bila kot
                                        zemljepisno osrednja jugoslovanska republikamed Hrvaško in
                                        Srbijo zaradi večnacionalne sestave prebivalstva
                                        neizbežnopoudarjena kot primer ohranjanja bratstva in
                                        enotnosti jugoslovanskih narodovin narodnosti. Prevladovalo
                                        je tudi mnenje, da bosanskohercegovski prostorpredstavlja
                                        srce obrambe pred zunanjo agresijo na Jugoslavijo in s tem
                                        najmočnejšegačuvaja komunistične oblasti. V kriznih
                                        osemdesetih letih je Bosno inHercegovino pretresalo nekaj
                                        gospodarskih afer in sodnih procesov, medtemko so
                                        jugoslovanski politični in gospodarski nesporazumi odsevali
                                        večinoma vnjenem vsakdanu, kjer je njena večnacionalnost
                                        predstavljala vse večjo težavo.Politični dogodki ob koncu
                                        osemdesetih in v začetku devetdesetih let 20.stoletja so
                                        bosanskohercegovsko družbo, kakršna se je oblikovala v
                                        socialističnemobdobju, tudi pripeljali do štiriletne vojne,
                                        v kateri so se zgodili številnivojni zločini, genocid in
                                        rušenje skupnih inštitucij bosanskohercegovskih oblastiin
                                        kulture. Čeprav se je agresija na na bosanskohercegovsko
                                        ozemlje pričelaže septembra 1991, je vojna izbruhnila 6.
                                        aprila 1992, na dan priznanjaneodvisnosti BiH. Vojna je le v
                                        enem letu (1993) prerasla v srbsko-bošnjaško27-hrvaški
                                        vojaški spopad, v delu Bosne pa celo v medbošnjaški. Do
                                        novembra1995 (Daytonski sporazum) je vojna vzela okoli sto
                                        tisoč življenj, pustila velikoštevilo invalidov in razselila
                                        številno prebivalstvo tako znotraj BiH kot tudi vinozemstvo.
                                        Danes Bosna in Hercegovina, ki je razdeljena oziroma jo
                                        sestavljatadve entiteti, odvisno od tolmačenja, spada med
                                        države Zahodnega Balkana.Ta predstavlja novonastali naziv za
                                        politično in gospodarsko neuspešne države.Iz današnje
                                        perspektive raziskovanje socialističnega obdobja v
                                        zgodoviniBosne in Hercegovine odpira številna vprašanja,
                                        vendar nanje domačem zgodovinopisjevečinoma ne ponuja
                                        odgovorov. V domači znanstveni javnosti sicerže od
                                        šestdesetih let obstaja ideja o izdelavi sintetične
                                        zgodovine Bosne in Hercegovine,vendar ta do danes še ni
                                        napisana.</p>
               </entity:description>
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The last two years of World War II were very important for
                                        Bosnia and Herzegovina,since the Communist Party of
                                        Yugoslavia did not understand its positionor doubted whether
                                        it should become an autonomous province or
                                        constitutiverepublic in the future socialist federation. At
                                        the second session of AVNOJ(Anti-Fascist Council of National
                                        Liberation of Yugoslavia) the question ofthe position of
                                        Bosnia and Herzegovina was solved. However, throughout
                                        thesocialist period the decisions and conclusions from the
                                        second session of ZAVNOBiH(State Anti-fascist Council for
                                        the National Liberation of Bosnia andHerzegovina) were
                                        referred to, and the date of 25 November 1943 (MrkonjićGrad)
                                        is the Statehood Day of Bosnia and Herzegovina. Today,
                                        though, it isonly celebrated in the parts of the federation
                                        of Bosnia and Herzegovina whereBosniak population is in the
                                        majority.In the socialist Yugoslavia, Bosnia and Herzegovina
                                        belonged to the groupof underdeveloped republics and
                                        depended on the financial resources from theUnderdeveloped
                                        Fund (federal fund for providing loans in order to
                                        facilitatethe development of economically underdeveloped
                                        republics and Kosovo). Untilthe mid-1960s it achieved
                                        important progress in all aspects. Furthermore, as
                                        the(geographically) central Yugoslav republic, located
                                        between Croatia and Serbia,it unavoidably represented a
                                        model of preserving the brotherhood and unityof the Yugoslav
                                        nations and nationalities due to its multi-national
                                        populationstructure. The opinion that Bosnian-Herzegovinian
                                        space represented the heartof the defence from any external
                                        aggression against Yugoslavia and that it wasthe strongest
                                        guard of the communist authorities was also prominent.
                                        During the1980s crisis Bosnia and Herzegovina was shaken by
                                        a few economic affairs andjudicial processes, but everyday
                                        life there was mostly affected by the Yugoslavpolitical and
                                        economic disagreements, and its multi-nationality
                                        represented anincreasingly severe problem.The political
                                        events at the end of the 1980s and in the beginning of the
                                        1990sinvolved the whole of Bosnian-Herzegovinian society,
                                        shaped during the socialistperiod, in a four-year war,
                                        during which numerous war crimes, genocide anddestruction of
                                        the common institutions of the Bosnian-Herzegovinian
                                        authoritiesand culture took place. Although aggression
                                        against the Bosnian-Herzegovinianterritory began already in
                                        September 1991, the war officially started on6 April 1992,
                                        on the day of the recognition of the Bosnian-Herzegovinian
                                        independence.In only one year (1993) this war developed into
                                        a military conflictbetween Serbs, Bosniaks and Croats, and
                                        in parts of Bosnia also in a conflictbetween Bosniaks. Until
                                        November 1995 (Dayton Agreement) this war claimedaround
                                        100,000 lives, resulted in a large number of persons with
                                        disabilities,and displaced the population within Bosnia and
                                        Herzegovina as well as beyondits borders. Today Bosnia and
                                        Herzegovina, divided into two entities, belongs– depending
                                        on the interpretation – among the states of the Western
                                        Balkans,which is the newly-coined expression for politically
                                        and economically unsuccessfulcountries.From today’s
                                        perspective the exploration of the socialist period in the
                                        historyof Bosnia and Herzegovina opens many questions, but
                                        Bosnian-Herzegovinianhistoriography does not possess
                                        well-founded answers for most of them. Eventhough in the
                                        Bosnian-Herzegovinian scientific community the idea of
                                        writingthe history of Bosnia and Herzegovina has existed
                                        since the 1960s, to date thishas not been achieved.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/jzVCJV8De80"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/20426"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.20497" ADMID="premis.20497 entity.20497">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
