<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37424"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-04-05T08:45:54"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-04-07T11:25:49"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.4" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37424" GROUPID="37424">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">From an Assistant to Equal Colleague. The Professionalization Process of the Teaching Profession for Female Teachers in Baden and Württemberg</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:creator>Godel Gaßner, Rosemarie</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">This research focuses on an analytical reconstruction and interpretation of the development of professionalization processes of the teaching profession for female teachers in the 19th and early 20th century in the two southwestern states of Germany. This period encompasses the integration of female teachers in the public school system, the development of different female teachers’ careers and their gradual adaptation to the education and training concepts of male teachers up to the days of the Weimar Republic. The category of gender and its relevance are addressed on a discourse level as well as on a level of strategic action and the issue of intentional control of state and non-state agents and their interdependencies is looked taking recourse to the term of control as it is used in political sciences. The professionalization process is presented within the range of top down processes dominated by government control measures and bottom up processes implemented for example by teachers’ associations. Despite striking similarities between the various courses of professionalizaton - especially in view of the state-initiated delay of the access of women to the public school system and the defensive attitude of teachers’ associations, they differ due to differences in education and training systems as well as the respective status of male teachers and their training and education concepts in both German states. The power of the church in matters of school supervision also plays an important role and so do the position of women in society generally and the status of girls’ education in particular.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history of female teachers</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">gender</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina ženskih učiteljev</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">spol</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Mislav Gregl (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2016-09-28</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37424">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37424</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37424</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37424">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng"> This research focuses on
                                    an analytical reconstruction and interpretation of the
                                    development of professionalization processes of the teaching
                                    profession for female teachers in the 19th and early 20th
                                    century in the two southwestern states of Germany. This period
                                    encompasses the integration of female teachers in the public
                                    school system, the development of different female teachers’
                                    careers and their gradual adaptation to the education and
                                    training concepts of male teachers up to the days of the Weimar
                                    Republic. The category of gender and its relevance are addressed
                                    on a discourse level as well as on a level of strategic action
                                    and the issue of intentional control of state and non-state
                                    agents and their interdependencies is looked taking recourse to
                                    the term of control as it is used in political sciences. The
                                    professionalization process is presented within the range of top
                                    down processes dominated by government control measures and
                                    bottom up processes implemented for example by teachers’
                                    associations. Despite striking similarities between the various
                                    courses of professionalizaton - especially in view of the
                                    state-initiated delay of the access of women to the public
                                    school system and the defensive attitude of teachers’
                                    associations, they differ due to differences in education and
                                    training systems as well as the respective status of male
                                    teachers and their training and education concepts in both
                                    German states. The power of the church in matters of school
                                    supervision also plays an important role and so do the position
                                    of women in society generally and the status of girls’ education
                                    in particular. </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RUEtASCmmbo"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37381"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37424" ADMID="premis.37424 entity.37424">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
