<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37704"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-31T11:09:13"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-16T10:57:11"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37704" GROUPID="37704">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Twenty years of activity of the Museum of Education (University of Padua)</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="ita">Vent’anni di attività al Museo dell’Educazione dell’Università di Padova</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Zamperlin, Patrizia</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The Museum of Education of Padua University was formally established in 1993 to collect, study and exhibit all materials related to the history of education, following males and females in and out of the school from birth to the adult life. Therefore, during its first twenty years of activity, the Museum of Education was first of all a place of scientific research, as evidenced by a lot of publications of national and international scholars who studied, in particular, the collections of textbooks and exercise books.Constant and parallel has been also the activity destined to the initial training of teachers and to the updating of those in service. To the teachers in training are destined specific workshops linked to the teaching of history of education both included in the degree course that prepares future teachers in primary schools; they find in the rich sorting out of experiences, and even in the mistakes that derive from the past, a firm anchorage for the construction of their professionalism. Besides, the teachers in training can follow the class during the visit; by observing the behavior of students in extracurricular contexts, they significantly integrate the skills matured during the training in the classroom. Initiatives of in-depth scientific analysis (often realized on the occasion of thematic exhibitions) and activities of methodological upgrade, especially with regard to the teaching of history, are addressed to teachers already operant. In the Museum's website (www.museo.educazione.unipd.it) you can see some of the materials prepared in internet documenting what has been done.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="ita">Il Museo dell’Educazione dell’Università degli Studi di Padova venne formalmente istituito nel 1993 per raccogliere, studiare ed esporre tutti i materiali relativi alla storia dell’educazione, seguendo maschi e femmine dentro e fuori la scuola dalla nascita all’ingresso nella vita adulta. In questi suoi primi vent’anni di attività il Museo è stato, innanzitutto, un luogo di ricerca scientifica come testimoniato da numerose pubblicazioni realizzate da studiosi italiani e stranieri che hanno attinto in particolare alle collezioni di libri di testo e di quaderni scolastici; costante e parallela è stata anche l’attività destinata alla formazione iniziale degli insegnanti e all’aggiornamento di quelli in servizio. Ai primi sono stati e sono destinati specifici laboratori legati agli insegnamenti di storia della scuola e di storia della pedagogia previsti nel corso di laurea che prepara i futuri docenti nella scuola primaria; essi trovano nella ricca sedimentazione di esperienze, e persino di errori che ricaviamo dal passato, un saldo ancoraggio per la costruzione della loro professionalità. Inoltre poter seguire seguire le scolaresche in visita osservando i comportamenti degli alunni in contesti extrascolastici integra significativamente le competenze che essi maturano nel tirocinio in aula. Agli insegnanti già in attività sono rivolte iniziative di approfondimento scientifico -spesso realizzate in occasione di mostre tematiche- e di aggiornamento metodologico-didattico, specie per quel che riguarda l’insegnamento della storia. Nel sito del Museo (www.museo.educazione.unipd.it) possono essere consultati alcuni dei materiali predisposti in rete per queste iniziative.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Simonetta Polenghi (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-28</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37704">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37704</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37704</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37704">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The Museum of Education of Padua University was formally
                                        established in 1993 to collect, study and exhibit all
                                        materials related to the history of education, following
                                        males and females in and out of the school from birth to the
                                        adult life. Therefore, during its first twenty years of
                                        activity, the Museum of Education was first of all a place
                                        of scientific research, as evidenced by a lot of
                                        publications of national and international scholars who
                                        studied, in particular, the collections of textbooks and
                                        exercise books.Constant and parallel has been also the
                                        activity destined to the initial training of teachers and to
                                        the updating of those in service. To the teachers in
                                        training are destined specific workshops linked to the
                                        teaching of history of education both included in the degree
                                        course that prepares future teachers in primary schools;
                                        they find in the rich sorting out of experiences, and even
                                        in the mistakes that derive from the past, a firm anchorage
                                        for the construction of their professionalism. Besides, the
                                        teachers in training can follow the class during the visit;
                                        by observing the behavior of students in extracurricular
                                        contexts, they significantly integrate the skills matured
                                        during the training in the classroom. Initiatives of
                                        in-depth scientific analysis (often realized on the occasion
                                        of thematic exhibitions) and activities of methodological
                                        upgrade, especially with regard to the teaching of history,
                                        are addressed to teachers already operant. In the Museum's
                                        website (www.museo.educazione.unipd.it) you can see some of
                                        the materials prepared in internet documenting what has been
                                        done.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/tE4alAvi3ac"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37702"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37704" ADMID="premis.37704 entity.37704">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
