<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37668"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-29T09:21:06"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-05-29T09:23:33"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Meden, Katja</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37668" GROUPID="37668">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">MUSLI: an integrated Museum from School to Children's Books</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="ita">Il MUSLI: un Museo integrato dalla Scuola alla Letteratura per l’Infanzia</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Mogavero, Francesca</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The Tancredi di Barolo Foundation, created in 2002 by Pompeo Vagliani, established the Museum of School and Children’s Literature in Palazzo Barolo Turin (Torino, Italy). In 2008 started the new Museum itinerary project, dedicated to Children’s Literature’s history, to complete the exposition about school’s history. The new Museum itinerary, branded MUSLI (Museo Scuola Libro Infanzia - Museum of School and Children’s Literature), was completed during the 150th Italy Unification celebrations and was inaugurated on 23rd of November 2011. The exposition valorizes the rich international historical fund, composed by 12 thousands items (books, original drawings, toys and games from XVIII to half XX centuries) and stored at Foundation’s archive and library. It is the most important centre dedicated to illustration and children’s and scholastic literature’s history on the territory open to the public. The new Museum itinerary is linked to the School Museum itinerary thanks to the presence in Palazzo Barolo, from 1869 to 1903, of the Eredi Botta Historical Typography, the third most important typographic factory of Turin in XIX century, that printed scholastic texts and reading books too; the recalling of Freinet scholastic typography and the exposition of school newspapers make another connection to School Museum itinerary. Indeed, the book theme has been always present in the School Museum itinerary, which particularly investigates the book Cuore written by Edmondo De Amicis, comparing past and present school (and literature), reality and imagination, persistently and in a captivating way. In the Book Museum itinerary the disability is particularly minded: under the banner “MUSLI: a Museum for everyone” a project has started with the purpose to grant an ever wider public the enjoyment of our patrimony, promoting an accessible knowledge of MUSLI collections and museum didactics.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="ita">La Fondazione Tancredi di Barolo, creata nel 2002 da Pompeo Vagliani, ha dato vita al Museo della scuola e del libro per l’infanzia di Palazzo Barolo (Torino, Italia). Nel 2008 ha avviato il progetto del nuovo percorso museale dedicato alla storia del libro per l’infanzia, a completamento dell’esposizione sulla storia della scuola. Il nuovo polo museale, con il nuovo marchio MUSLI (Museo Scuola Libro Infanzia) è stato completato nell’ambito delle manifestazioni per i 150 anni dell’Unità d’Italia e inaugurato il 23 Novembre 2011. L’esposizione valorizza il ricco fondo storico internazionale di 12000 pezzi (libri, disegni originali, giochi dal Settecento alla metà del Novecento) conservato presso l’archivio e la biblioteca della Fondazione. Si tratta del nucleo più importante legato alla storia dell’illustrazione e della letteratura per l’infanzia e scolastica presente sul territorio a disposizione del pubblico. Il nuovo polo museale si ricollega a quello già consolidato ricordando la presenza a Palazzo Barolo, dal 1869 al 1903, della Tipografia Eredi Botta, la terza industria tipografica di Torino nell’Ottocento, che produceva anche testi scolastici e di lettura; un ulteriore legame con il Percorso Scuola è costituito dalla ricostruzione della Tipografia scolastica Freinet e dall’esposizione dei giornalini di classe. Il tema del libro, d’altra parte, è da sempre integrato all’interno del Percorso Scuola, che approfondisce in particolar modo il libro Cuore di De Amicis, operando un costante e coinvolgente confronto tra scuola (e letteratura) di ieri e di oggi, tra scuola immaginaria e scuola reale. Nel Percorso Libro, particolare attenzione è rivolta al tema della Disabilità: sotto il titolo “Il MUSLI: un Museo per tutti”, è stato avviato infatti un progetto volto a garantire la fruizione del nostro patrimonio a una fascia sempre più ampia di pubblico, promuovendo una conoscenza accessibile delle collezioni del MUSLI e della didattica museale.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Mathias Rösch (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-27</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37668">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37668</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37668</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37668">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <pre xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The Tancredi di Barolo Foundation, created in 2002 by Pompeo Vagliani, established the Museum of
School and Children’s Literature in Palazzo Barolo Turin (Torino, Italy). In 2008 started the new Museum
itinerary project, dedicated to Children’s Literature’s history, to complete the exposition about school’s history.
The new Museum itinerary, branded MUSLI (Museo Scuola Libro Infanzia - Museum of School and Children’s
Literature), was completed during the 150th Italy Unification celebrations and was inaugurated on 23rd of
November 2011.
The exposition valorizes the rich international historical fund, composed by 12 thousands items (books,
original drawings, toys and games from XVIII to half XX centuries) and stored at Foundation’s archive and
library. It is the most important centre dedicated to illustration and children’s and scholastic literature’s history
on the territory open to the public.
The new Museum itinerary is linked to the School Museum itinerary thanks to the presence in Palazzo
Barolo, from 1869 to 1903, of the Eredi Botta Historical Typography, the third most important typographic
factory of Turin in XIX century, that printed scholastic texts and reading books too; the recalling of Freinet
scholastic typography and the exposition of school newspapers make another connection to School Museum
itinerary.
Indeed, the book theme has been always present in the School Museum itinerary, which particularly
investigates the book Cuore written by Edmondo De Amicis, comparing past and present school (and literature),
reality and imagination, persistently and in a captivating way. In the Book Museum itinerary the disability is
particularly minded: under the banner “MUSLI: a Museum for everyone” a project has started with the purpose
to grant an ever wider public the enjoyment of our patrimony, promoting an accessible knowledge of MUSLI
collections and museum didactics.</pre>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/ktf0PS7wa9A"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37663"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37668" ADMID="premis.37668 entity.37668">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
