<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37678"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-29T11:26:17"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-05-29T11:27:53"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37678" GROUPID="37678">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Evolution of the French National Museum of Education, Rouen</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="fra">Evolution du musée national de l’Education, Rouen</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Campagnolle, Delphine</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">Since the 13th Symposium in 2009 that took place in Rouen, the national Museum of education knew big evolutions. First of all, collections renovation, planned for the moving of the museum, finished in 2011. The architectural planning of the 6 street of Bihorel offered the museum a remarkable place for preventive conservation and research. The contemporary architecture, designed by the studio of N.Fahmy, includes not only the collections (950 000 items) but also the scientific and the documentary activities. So five reserves on about 2600 meters square conserve collections according to different typologies and materials, since the textbooks and the literature youth until pupil writing desks, photos, games and toys, lantern slides, etc. The key point of our documentation centre is certainly the possibility for researchers, teachers, students to see and study the originals works of art and originals documents which arrive directly from the reserve toward the study room. This access is permitted also thanks to our database and our web site, actually in revision. To date, half of the collections is digitized. This profound restructuration was also an institutional change since the dissolution of the INRP in 2010. By decree, the national museum of education was integrated since the 1st of January 2011 to the Centre national de Documentation Pédagogique (CNDP). This change of supervision offers new opportunities. Indeed, the scientific activity and the Research are maintained but also the national museum benefits from CNDP network, that counts one centre in each region of France (Centre Régional de Documentation Pédagogique, CRDP). We could imagine itinerant exhibitions all over the territory and also new ways of meeting people. At last, the expertise of the CNDP about digital technology used in education will help us to think about the digital creation in museums and become a ”digital museum”. An association “ Friends of the National Museum of Education” was born in 2011 compound of teachers, researchers, professionals of education and culture. The driving force behind this association allowed the entrances of news collections.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="fra">Le musée national de l’Education depuis le symposium qui s’est tenu en 2009 à Rouen a connu de grandes évolutions. Tout d’abord le chantier des collections qui était en oeuvre en vue du déménagement des collections s’est achevé en 2011. Les travaux engagés sur le site du 6 rue de Bihorel offrent au musée aujourd’hui un outil muséographique remarquable. Un bâtiment contemporain, oeuvre du cabinet de l’architecte N. Fahmy regroupe aujourd’hui les collections (950 000 items) mais aussi les activités scientifiques et documentaires du musée. Ainsi, sur 2600 mètres carrés, 5 réserves conservent les collections par typologie d’objets, depuis les manuels scolaires et les ouvrages de littérature jeunesse jusqu’aux pupitres des écoliers, en passant par les collections de photographies, de jeux et de jouets, de vues sur verre etc. Le point fort de notre établissement est d’offrir aujourd’hui une salle d’étude qui permette aux chercheurs, aux étudiants, aux enseignants de consulter les oeuvres d’art et documents originaux. Cet accès aux collections est enrichi d’une base de données en cours de refonte, consultable depuis le site internet du musée, couvrant à ce jour la moitié des collections du musée. Cette profonde reconfiguration s’est vue accompagner d’un changement institutionnel, puisque le musée national de l’Education, suite à la dissolution de l’INRP en 2010 a été rattaché par décret au Centre National de Documentation Pédagogique. Ce changement de tutelle offre de nouvelles opportunités. Si en effet, l'activité scientifique et de recherche est maintenue, le musée national de l’Education ne pouvait pas disposer d’un maillage plus adapté sur le territoire, grâce notamment aux relais que composent les CRDP, pour bénéficier de possibilités nouvelles en termes d’itinérance d’expositions et d'élargissement des publics. Enfin, l’expertise du CNDP concernant le numérique éducatif offre des possibilités nouvelles pour inscrire le MNE dans une réflexion actuelle portant sur le musée numérique. Enfin, une association des amis du musée national de l’Education a vu le jour en 2011 composée d’enseignants, de chercheurs, de professionnels de l’Education et du patrimoine. Force de proposition, cette association a permis l’entrée de fonds remarqués dans les collections.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Tijs van Ruiten (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-27</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37678">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37678</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37678</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37678">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <pre xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">Since the 13th Symposium in 2009 that took place in Rouen, the national Museum of education knew
big evolutions. First of all, collections renovation, planned for the moving of the museum, finished in 2011. The architectural planning of the 6 street of Bihorel offered the museum a remarkable place for preventive
conservation and research. The contemporary architecture, designed by the studio of N.Fahmy, includes not
only the collections (950 000 items) but also the scientific and the documentary activities.
So five reserves on about 2600 meters square conserve collections according to different typologies and
materials, since the textbooks and the literature youth until pupil writing desks, photos, games and toys, lantern
slides, etc.
The key point of our documentation centre is certainly the possibility for researchers, teachers, students
to see and study the originals works of art and originals documents which arrive directly from the reserve
toward the study room. This access is permitted also thanks to our database and our web site, actually in
revision. To date, half of the collections is digitized.
This profound restructuration was also an institutional change since the dissolution of the INRP in 2010.
By decree, the national museum of education was integrated since the 1st of January 2011 to the Centre national
de Documentation Pédagogique (CNDP).
This change of supervision offers new opportunities. Indeed, the scientific activity and the Research are
maintained but also the national museum benefits from CNDP network, that counts one centre in each region of
France (Centre Régional de Documentation Pédagogique, CRDP). We could imagine itinerant exhibitions all
over the territory and also new ways of meeting people. At last, the expertise of the CNDP about digital
technology used in education will help us to think about the digital creation in museums and become a ”digital
museum”.
An association “ Friends of the National Museum of Education” was born in 2011 compound of
teachers, researchers, professionals of education and culture. The driving force behind this association allowed
the entrances of news collections.</pre>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/ChS0acphhwA"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37676"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37678" ADMID="premis.37678 entity.37678">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
