<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37689"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-29T12:23:31"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-16T10:53:00"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Meden, Katja</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37689" GROUPID="37689">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Using Museums as an Educational Resource for the Mentally Disabled: A Case Example</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="tur">Zihinsel engelliler için müzelerin bir eğitim kaynağı olarak kullanımı: Bir uygulama örneği</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Nezehat Saraç, Çağla</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The object of this paper is to share the results of a museological study which involved the planning and realization of an educational program for a group of mentally disabled students. The aim of the study was to research relative literature on special groups’ and their teachers’ experiences at the museum; and then to create, put into practice and evaluate the outcomes of an exemplary educational program. Having completed this in 2002, the author, after ten years, is to now follow-up on the long-term effects of the educational program on the parties involved. The parties to be interviewed are the group of students which have taken part in the program, the particular museum’s current personnel at which part of the program had taken place, and the personnel of the special educational institute at also which part of the program had taken place. The methodology of the study had included literature review, educational program development, interviews, in-class presentations and discussions, trip to and exercises at the museum, and drama. The results of the study are cataloged as written and visual material produced by the group of students who have participated in the program. These are to be presented as a ppt. along with personal observations and evaluation of the author. Overall, the paper will attempt to show how museums may be used as places for social integration and life-long personal development for the mentally disabled. It will also try to measure ‘learning’ in the long term on the parties involved.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="tur">Bu makalenin amacı, zihinsel engelli bir öğrenci grubu için planlanan ve uygulanan eğitim programını içeren müzeolojik çalışmanın sonuçlarını paylaşmaktır . Çalışmanın amacı, özel grupların ve onların eğitmenlerinin müze deneyimleri hakkında literatür taraması yapmak, ve örnek olabilecek bir müze eğitim programı yaratmak, uygulamak ve sonuçlarını değerlendirmek idi. 2002 yılında tamamlanan çalışmadan on yıl sonra yazar, çalışmaya katılan grup ve kurumlar üzerinde eğitim programının uzun dönem etkilerini izleyecektir. Mülakat yapılacak gruplar, programa katılmış olan öğrenci grubu, çalışmanın gerçekleştirildiği müze ve özel eğitim kurumunun bugünkü çalışanları olacaktır. Çalışmanın tamamlanmış kısmında metodoloji, literatür taraması, eğitim programı geliştirme, mülakatlar, sınıf içi sunumlar ve tartışmalar, müze ziyareti ve uygulamaları, ve drama çalışmasını kapsamıştır. Çalışmanın sonuçları, programa katılan öğrenciler tarafından üretilmiş yaz ılı ve görsel malzeme olmak üzere kataloglandırılmıştır. Bu malzeme, yazarın kişisel gözlemleri ve değerlendirmesi ile birlikte sunulacaktır. Bütününde makalemiz, müzelerin, zihinsel engellilerin sosyal entegrasyonu ve hayat boyu kişisel gelişiminde bir me kan olarak nasıl kullanılabileceğini göstermeye teşebbüs etmektedir. Ayrıca katılımcı, tarafların uzun vadede 'öğrenimlerini' ölçmeye çalışacaktır.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Delphine Campagolle (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-27</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37689">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37689</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37689</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37689">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The object of this paper is to share the results of a
                                        museological study which involved the planning and
                                        realization of an educational program for a group of
                                        mentally disabled students. The aim of the study was to
                                        research relative literature on special groups’ and their
                                        teachers’ experiences at the museum; and then to create, put
                                        into practice and evaluate the outcomes of an exemplary
                                        educational program. Having completed this in 2002, the
                                        author, after ten years, is to now follow-up on the
                                        long-term effects of the educational program on the parties
                                        involved. The parties to be interviewed are the group of
                                        students which have taken part in the program, the
                                        particular museum’s current personnel at which part of the
                                        program had taken place, and the personnel of the special
                                        educational institute at also which part of the program had
                                        taken place. The methodology of the study had included
                                        literature review, educational program development,
                                        interviews, in-class presentations and discussions, trip to
                                        and exercises at the museum, and drama. The results of the
                                        study are cataloged as written and visual material produced
                                        by the group of students who have participated in the
                                        program. These are to be presented as a ppt. along with
                                        personal observations and evaluation of the author. Overall,
                                        the paper will attempt to show how museums may be used as
                                        places for social integration and life-long personal
                                        development for the mentally disabled. It will also try to
                                        measure ‘learning’ in the long term on the parties
                                        involved.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/jnjf39SDDxI"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37686"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37689" ADMID="premis.37689 entity.37689">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
