<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37733"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-06-12T11:25:01"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-12T11:27:01"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37733" GROUPID="37733">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Thurgovian Pioneers of the Science Experiments Kit</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="deu">Thurgauer Pioniere des Experimentierkastens</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Oettli, Andreas</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">In our presentation we want to portray the life work of five teachers who in the first half of the 20th century not only recognized the need for holistic and autonomous learning but promoted it in a decisive way. All five of them developed tools for teaching - albeit in individual ways - and thereby contributed crucially to the quality and the process of modernisation of our schools. Starting from their point of action in the canton of Thurgau in Northeastern Switzerland, they gained both national and international recognition. Johannes Eberli (1860 - 1928) was a science professor at a school for future teachers and developed a Science Experiments Kit for primary and secondary school, accompanied by a practical instruction manual. August Bach (1869 - 1950) founded a correctional school and succeeded in turning it into a model school. He developed teaching tools and measuring instruments for mathematics and physics classes in primary and secondary school. Wilhelm Fröhlich (1892 - 1969) gained worldwide recognition for his KOSMOS Science Experiments Kits for school and home. Paul Eggmann (1904 -1985) came up with a system to build your own Science Experiments Kits and for decades, shared his ideas with scores of other teachers. Eugen Knup (1898 - 1987) was fascinated by the radio. He wrote instructions and developed gadgets to promote knowledge about the physical and technical basics of this new medium. The main focus of the presentation will be on August Bach and Wilhelm Fröhlich. The School Museum of Amriswil is dedicating a publication with the title "Thurgovian Pioneers of the Science Experimenting Kits" to those five school teachers.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="deu">Das Referat gibt Einblick in das Lebenswerk von fünf Lehrern, welche in der ersten Hälfte des 20. Jahrhunderts den Bedarf nach ganzheitlicher Bildung und selbsttätigem Lernen erkannt und in eindrücklicher Weise gefördert haben. Sie alle haben, wenn auch in verschiedener Weise, Lehrmittel entwickelt und damit wesentlich zur Qualität und Modernisierung unserer Schulen beigetragen. Ausgehend von ihrem Wirkungsort im Kanton Thurgau, in der Nordostschweiz, haben sie national und teils international Bedeutung erlangt. Johannes Eberli (1860–1928) entwickelte als Seminarlehrer für Naturwissenschaften ein Experimentierset für Volksschulklassen und verfasste eine praktische Anleitung dazu. August Bach (1869–1950) gründete ein Landerziehungsheim als Musterschule und entwickelte Lehrmittel und Messgeräte für den Mathematik- und Physikunterricht der Volksschule. Wilhelm Fröhlich (1892–1969) erlangte weltweite Anerkennung für seine KOSMOS– Experimentierkästen für Schule und Haus. Paul Eggmann (1904–1985) entwickelte ein System zum Eigenbau von Experimentiergeräten und vermittelte seine Ideen jahrzehntelang in Lehrerbildungskursen. Eugen Knup (1898–1987) war angetan vom Medium Radio. Er verfasste Schriften und entwickelte Lehrgeräte zur Vermittlung der physikalischen und technischen Grundlagen dieses neuen Mediums. Der Hauptteil des Vortrags gilt August Bach und Wilhelm Fröhlich. Das Schulmuseum in Amriswil hat diesen Schulmännern eine Publikation gewidmet mit dem Titel „Thurgauer Pioniere des Experimentierkastens“.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Mathias Rösch (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-28</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">deu</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37733">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37733</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37733</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37733">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">In our presentation we want to portray the life work of five
                                        teachers who in the first half of the 20th century not only
                                        recognized the need for holistic and autonomous learning but
                                        promoted it in a decisive way. All five of them developed
                                        tools for teaching - albeit in individual ways - and thereby
                                        contributed crucially to the quality and the process of
                                        modernisation of our schools. Starting from their point of
                                        action in the canton of Thurgau in Northeastern Switzerland,
                                        they gained both national and international recognition.
                                        Johannes Eberli (1860 - 1928) was a science professor at a
                                        school for future teachers and developed a Science
                                        Experiments Kit for primary and secondary school,
                                        accompanied by a practical instruction manual. August Bach
                                        (1869 - 1950) founded a correctional school and succeeded in
                                        turning it into a model school. He developed teaching tools
                                        and measuring instruments for mathematics and physics
                                        classes in primary and secondary school. Wilhelm Fröhlich
                                        (1892 - 1969) gained worldwide recognition for his KOSMOS
                                        Science Experiments Kits for school and home. Paul Eggmann
                                        (1904 -1985) came up with a system to build your own Science
                                        Experiments Kits and for decades, shared his ideas with
                                        scores of other teachers. Eugen Knup (1898 - 1987) was
                                        fascinated by the radio. He wrote instructions and developed
                                        gadgets to promote knowledge about the physical and
                                        technical basics of this new medium. The main focus of the
                                        presentation will be on August Bach and Wilhelm Fröhlich.
                                        The School Museum of Amriswil is dedicating a publication
                                        with the title "Thurgovian Pioneers of the Science
                                        Experimenting Kits" to those five school teachers.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/IX-XdAO1waI"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37731"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37733" ADMID="premis.37733 entity.37733">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
