<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/14267"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2012-11-30T16:18:38"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-02-09T10:49:39"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Meden, Katja</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.14267" GROUPID="14267">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="slv">Represija nad pripadnicima njemačke manjine u Hrvatskoj, Bosni i Hercegovini i Vojvodini, 1944.–1948.</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="eng">Repression against the Members of the German Minority in Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and Vojvodina 1944–1948</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Geiger, Vladimir</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="eng">Due to the wartime developments, until the end of World War II the majorityof Germans living in Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina and Vojvodina had fledor been driven from their homes, mostly to Austria and Germany where they also awaited the end of the war. Only those Germans not in immediate danger because of the war remained home. However, at the end of 1944 and in the beginning of 1945 a systematic persecution of the remaining ethnic Germans(»Volksdeutche«) in Yugoslavia was initiated by the partisan movement and the newly established people’s authorities. In particular, the decision of the Presidency of AVNOJ (Anti-Fascist Council of National Liberation of Yugoslavia)of 21 November 1944, pronouncing the members of the German minority as collectively guilty, contributed to this. War crimes perpetrated by some of the Yugoslav ethnic Germans and their disloyalty during the occupation served asa reason and justify caution for the inhuman actions taken against the German minorityat the end of the war and in the post-war period. During the wartime operations and immediately after them the German inhabitants who failed to escape were at the mercy of the victors. After the war the Yugoslav communist authorities confiscated the property of the members of the German minority and took away their national and citizen rights. Those Yugoslav Germans who could prove that they had participated in the partisan movementor supported it were not among the victims of collective retaliation. Immediately after the war the Yugoslav communist authorities prohibited the return of ethnic Germans who had escaped or been exiled, while those of them still in Yugoslavia were to be deported from the country and were interned into the repatriation camps. As the deportation of the ethnic Germans from Yugoslavia was, in the summer of 1945, prevented by the closing of the Austrian-Yugoslav border by the Allied occupation authorities, who opposed the Yugoslav intentions, most of the Volksdeutsche ended up in the camps, condemned to several years of forced labour. After the camps had been abolished and the prisoners had been released, in the 1950s the majority of Germans from Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina and Vojvodina moved to Austria and Germany because of their difficult position and lack of any prospects in Yugoslavia. The attitude of the partisan movement and the »people’s« authorities towards the Yugoslav Germans, legally declared as collectively guilty, is an evident example of ethnic cleansingin Yugoslavia at the end of World War II and in the immediate post-war period.</dcterms:abstract>
            <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="hrv">Do potkraj Drugoga svjetskog rata većina hrvatskih, bosansko-hercegovačkihi vojvođanskih Nijemaca, uslijed ratnih događanja, izbjegla je ili je protjeranaiz svojih domova, pretežito u Austriju i Njemačku, gdje su i dočekali završetak rata. U zavičaju su ostali mahom oni Nijemci koji nisu bili izloženine posrednoj ratnoj opasnosti. No, potkraj 1944. i početkom 1945. počinje odstrane partizanskog pokreta i novo uspostavljenih narodnih vlasti sustavan progon preostalih folksdojčera u Jugoslaviji. Tome je napose pridonijela i odluka Predsjedništva AVNOJ-a od 21. studenoga 1944., koja je pripadnike njemačke manjine proglasila kolektivnim krivcima. Ratni zločini koje je dio jugoslavenskih folksdojčera počinio, te njihovo nelojalno držanje tijekom okupacije, poslužilisu i kao razlog i kao opravdanje za neljudsko postupanje sa njemačkom manjinom potkraj i nakon rata. Njemačko stanovništvo, koje nije izbjeglo, bilo je tijekom i neposredno nakonratnih djelovanja prepušteno samovolji pobjednika. Nakon rata komunistička vlast u Jugoslaviji pripadnicima njemačke manjine konfiscirala je imovinu i oduzela nacionalna i građanska prava. Žrtve kolektivne odmazde nisu bili oni jugoslavenski Nijemci koji su mogli dokazati sudjelovanje u partizanskom pokretuili njegovo potpomaganje. U neposrednom poraću jugoslavenske komunističkevlasti su zauzele stajalište o zabrani povratka izbjeglih i protjeranih folksdojčera, a one preostale u Jugoslaviji namjeravale su protjerati iz zemlje,te su ih internirali u logore za repatrijaciju. Kako je protjerivanje folksdojčeraiz Jugoslavije zbog zatvaranja austrijsko-jugoslavenske granice od strane savezničkihokupacijskih vlasti u ljeto 1945., koje su iskazivale protivljenje jugoslavenskimnastojanjima, to onemogućilo za većinu folksdojčera slijede logorii višegodišnji prisilni rad. Nakon ukidanja logora i puštanja na slobodu, najvećibroj hrvatskih, bosansko-hercegovačkih i vojvođanskih Nijemaca je zbog svogapoložaja i bezperspektivnosti u Jugoslaviji, tijekom pedesetih godina 20. stoljećaiselio u Austriju i Njemačku. Odnos partizanskog pokreta i »narodnih« vlastiprema jugoslavenskim Nijemcima, kojima je pripisana i ozakonjena kolektivnakrivnja, ogledni je primjer etničkoga čišćenja u Jugoslaviji potkraj Drugogasvjetskog rata i u neposrednom poraću.</dcterms:abstract>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino/Institute of Contemporary History, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2012-11-07</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">hrv</dcterms:language>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.14267">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>14267</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/14267</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.14267">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="slv">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">Do potkraj Drugoga svjetskog rata većina hrvatskih,
                                        bosansko-hercegovačkihi vojvođanskih Nijemaca, uslijed
                                        ratnih događanja, izbjegla je ili je protjeranaiz svojih
                                        domova, pretežito u Austriju i Njemačku, gdje su i dočekali
                                        završetak rata. U zavičaju su ostali mahom oni Nijemci koji
                                        nisu bili izloženine posrednoj ratnoj opasnosti. No, potkraj
                                        1944. i početkom 1945. počinje odstrane partizanskog pokreta
                                        i novo uspostavljenih narodnih vlasti sustavan progon
                                        preostalih folksdojčera u Jugoslaviji. Tome je napose
                                        pridonijela i odluka Predsjedništva AVNOJ-a od 21. studenoga
                                        1944., koja je pripadnike njemačke manjine proglasila
                                        kolektivnim krivcima. Ratni zločini koje je dio
                                        jugoslavenskih folksdojčera počinio, te njihovo nelojalno
                                        držanje tijekom okupacije, poslužilisu i kao razlog i kao
                                        opravdanje za neljudsko postupanje sa njemačkom manjinom
                                        potkraj i nakon rata. Njemačko stanovništvo, koje nije
                                        izbjeglo, bilo je tijekom i neposredno nakonratnih
                                        djelovanja prepušteno samovolji pobjednika. Nakon rata
                                        komunistička vlast u Jugoslaviji pripadnicima njemačke
                                        manjine konfiscirala je imovinu i oduzela nacionalna i
                                        građanska prava. Žrtve kolektivne odmazde nisu bili oni
                                        jugoslavenski Nijemci koji su mogli dokazati sudjelovanje u
                                        partizanskom pokretuili njegovo potpomaganje. U neposrednom
                                        poraću jugoslavenske komunističkevlasti su zauzele
                                        stajalište o zabrani povratka izbjeglih i protjeranih
                                        folksdojčera, a one preostale u Jugoslaviji namjeravale su
                                        protjerati iz zemlje,te su ih internirali u logore za
                                        repatrijaciju. Kako je protjerivanje folksdojčeraiz
                                        Jugoslavije zbog zatvaranja austrijsko-jugoslavenske granice
                                        od strane savezničkihokupacijskih vlasti u ljeto 1945., koje
                                        su iskazivale protivljenje jugoslavenskimnastojanjima, to
                                        onemogućilo za većinu folksdojčera slijede logorii
                                        višegodišnji prisilni rad. Nakon ukidanja logora i puštanja
                                        na slobodu, najvećibroj hrvatskih, bosansko-hercegovačkih i
                                        vojvođanskih Nijemaca je zbog svogapoložaja i
                                        bezperspektivnosti u Jugoslaviji, tijekom pedesetih godina
                                        20. stoljećaiselio u Austriju i Njemačku. Odnos partizanskog
                                        pokreta i »narodnih« vlastiprema jugoslavenskim Nijemcima,
                                        kojima je pripisana i ozakonjena kolektivnakrivnja, ogledni
                                        je primjer etničkoga čišćenja u Jugoslaviji potkraj
                                        Drugogasvjetskog rata i u neposrednom poraću.</p>
               </entity:description>
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">Due to the wartime developments, until the end of World War
                                        II the majorityof Germans living in Croatia, Bosnia and
                                        Herzegovina and Vojvodina had fledor been driven from their
                                        homes, mostly to Austria and Germany where they also awaited
                                        the end of the war. Only those Germans not in immediate
                                        danger because of the war remained home. However, at the end
                                        of 1944 and in the beginning of 1945 a systematic
                                        persecution of the remaining ethnic Germans(»Volksdeutche«)
                                        in Yugoslavia was initiated by the partisan movement and the
                                        newly established people’s authorities. In particular, the
                                        decision of the Presidency of AVNOJ (Anti-Fascist Council of
                                        National Liberation of Yugoslavia)of 21 November 1944,
                                        pronouncing the members of the German minority as
                                        collectively guilty, contributed to this. War crimes
                                        perpetrated by some of the Yugoslav ethnic Germans and their
                                        disloyalty during the occupation served asa reason and
                                        justify caution for the inhuman actions taken against the
                                        German minorityat the end of the war and in the post-war
                                        period. During the wartime operations and immediately after
                                        them the German inhabitants who failed to escape were at the
                                        mercy of the victors. After the war the Yugoslav communist
                                        authorities confiscated the property of the members of the
                                        German minority and took away their national and citizen
                                        rights. Those Yugoslav Germans who could prove that they had
                                        participated in the partisan movementor supported it were
                                        not among the victims of collective retaliation. Immediately
                                        after the war the Yugoslav communist authorities prohibited
                                        the return of ethnic Germans who had escaped or been exiled,
                                        while those of them still in Yugoslavia were to be deported
                                        from the country and were interned into the repatriation
                                        camps. As the deportation of the ethnic Germans from
                                        Yugoslavia was, in the summer of 1945, prevented by the
                                        closing of the Austrian-Yugoslav border by the Allied
                                        occupation authorities, who opposed the Yugoslav intentions,
                                        most of the Volksdeutsche ended up in the camps, condemned
                                        to several years of forced labour. After the camps had been
                                        abolished and the prisoners had been released, in the 1950s
                                        the majority of Germans from Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina
                                        and Vojvodina moved to Austria and Germany because of their
                                        difficult position and lack of any prospects in Yugoslavia.
                                        The attitude of the partisan movement and the »people’s«
                                        authorities towards the Yugoslav Germans, legally declared
                                        as collectively guilty, is an evident example of ethnic
                                        cleansingin Yugoslavia at the end of World War II and in the
                                        immediate post-war period.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/embed/ytXUTSEODTg"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/14256"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.14267" ADMID="premis.14267 entity.14267">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
