<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37653"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-25T11:07:05"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-05-25T11:10:31"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37653" GROUPID="37653">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Leipzig teachers association (1846-2013)</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="deu">Leipziger Lehrerverein (1846-2013)</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Urban, Elke</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The lipsian teacher association has been forbidden twice in the 20th century and nowadays just a few experts know about the outstanding history of this association. In all its efforts the mental und physical balance of city kids took center, to ease their “joylessness of their childhood”. The far beyond city limits procreative acting, to give children consideration to education, had a sudden end in times of National Socialism 1933 and Stalinism after 1945. At the 10th April in 1933 the closure of the lipsian teacher association was commanded caused by the consolidation of institutional powers. At the second time it has been broken down just after its reestablishment. From that moment on every innovative idea was supposed to be realised in a so named “Einheitsgewerkschaft”. This very explicit voice that often went against the flow finally became silent till 1990. Nowadays the association has not to fight against dictatorship anymore but against a high quantity of national associations. There are many reasons to look up to the nationwide impression and mental autonomy of this association. From the very beginning the lipsian teacher association has been exemplary tor the education policy and educational work. Its been fighting for reformation of religious education, asked for a comprehensive schools, argued the abandonment of physical caning, sent a reminder about the disestablishment of church and school and was struggling with passion for the social equal treatment of elementary teachers. It also rendered outstanding services in advancement of educational science and methodology. The lipsian teacher association had 16 departments and almost twice as much scientific committees. These days there is no need to fight for educational freedom rights but they must be lived so they do not wither.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="deu">Der Leipziger Lehrerverein wurde im 20. Jahrhundert zweimal verboten und nur wenige Experten wissen noch etwas über seine bedeutende Geschichte. Bei all seinen Bemühungen stand das geistige und körperliche Gleichgewicht der Großstadtkinder, das Mildern der „Freudlosigkeit ihrer Kindheit“ im Mittelpunkt. Sein weit über Leipzigs Stadtgrenzen hinaus fruchtbares Wirken für eine dem Kind gerecht werdende Pädagogik fand im Nationalsozialismus 1933 und im Stalinismus nach 1945 zweimal ein jähes Ende. Am 10. April 1933 wurde im Zuge der Gleichschaltung die Auflösung des LLV angeordnet. Ein zweites Mal wurde der LLV 1946 kurz nach der Neugründung wieder aufgelöst mit der Maßgabe, dass nun alle fortschrittlichen Ideen in der neuen Einheitsgewerkschaft verwirklicht würden. Die deutliche, oft auch gerade gegen den Strom schwimmende Stimme aus Leipzig verstummte bis 1990. In der Gegenwart kämpft dieser Verein nicht mehr gegen eine Diktatur, aber gegen eine zahlenmäßige Überlegenheit großer Landesverbände. Es gibt genug Gründe, die überregionale Strahlkraft und die geistige Unabhängigkeit dieses Vereins zu bewundern. Von Anfang an leistete der LLV Vorbildliches für die schulpolitische und pädagogische Arbeit. So kämpfte er um eine Erneuerung des Religionsunterrichtes, forderte die Einheitsschule, diskutierte den Verzicht auf das Züchtigungsrecht, mahnte die strikte Trennung von Kirche und Schule an und bemühte sich leidenschaftlich darum, die soziale und gesellschaftliche Stellung der Volksschullehrer zu verbessern. Auch um die Weiterentwicklung pädagogischer Wissenschaft und Methodik machte sich der LLV verdient. Er unterhielt 16 wissenschaftliche Abteilungen und fast doppelt so viele wissenschaftliche Ausschüsse. Pädagogische Freiheitsrechte müssen heute nicht mehr erkämpft, aber dennoch gelebt werden, damit sie nicht verkümmern.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Ulla Nitsch (moderator</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-26</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37653">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37653</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37653</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37653">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <pre xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The lipsian teacher association has been forbidden twice in the 20th century and nowadays just a few
experts know about the outstanding history of this association. In all its efforts the mental und physical balance
of city kids took center, to ease their “joylessness of their childhood”. The far beyond city limits procreative
acting, to give children consideration to education, had a sudden end in times of National Socialism 1933 and
Stalinism after 1945.
At the 10th April in 1933 the closure of the lipsian teacher association was commanded caused by the
consolidation of institutional powers. At the second time it has been broken down just after its reestablishment.
From that moment on every innovative idea was supposed to be realised in a so named “Einheitsgewerkschaft”.
This very explicit voice that often went against the flow finally became silent till 1990.
Nowadays the association has not to fight against dictatorship anymore but against a high quantity of
national associations. There are many reasons to look up to the nationwide impression and mental autonomy of
this association. From the very beginning the lipsian teacher association has been exemplary tor the education
policy and educational work. Its been fighting for reformation of religious education, asked for a comprehensive
schools, argued the abandonment of physical caning, sent a reminder about the disestablishment of church and
school and was struggling with passion for the social equal treatment of elementary teachers. It also rendered
outstanding services in advancement of educational science and methodology. The lipsian teacher association
had 16 departments and almost twice as much scientific committees. These days there is no need to fight for
educational freedom rights but they must be lived so they do not wither.</pre>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/67w3gFi40NE"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37650"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37653" ADMID="premis.37653 entity.37653">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
