<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37657"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-25T11:46:00"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-05-25T11:49:56"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Meden, Katja</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37657" GROUPID="37657">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">On the image of teacher in the exhibition at school museum</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="jpn">学校博物館の展示における教師像</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Inokuchi, Junzo</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">There is the restoration of classroom at almost school museum. It is instructive for students to understand the history of the school. But we cannot find the image of teacher there. For example there are 5 classrooms in the National School Museum in Rotterdam: the village school of 1662, the model school in 1830, classroom of 1910, classroom of 1930, classroom of 1960. But there is only one teacher in the village school of 1662 and it is reconstructed from a painting by the famous 17th century Dutch painter Adriaen van Ostade. This picture is able to be seen in the Louvre. There are 3 classrooms in the School Museum in Dresden: in the German Empire (1871-1918), in the Weimar Republic(1919-1933) and in the German Democratic Republic(1949-1990). But we cannot find the image of teacher also. We can find the image of teacher at the toy museum rather than at the school museum. It is the miniature and only male teacher. There are few women teachers. We cannot find the teachers’ gatherings also at the school museum. I have visited to the school museum or toy museum in Holland, in England, in Germany, in Austria, in Switzerland, in Czech, in Korea and in Japan, but it is the same conditions. It is difficult to imagine the activity of teachers. I think that the reason is the reflection of historical and social conditions. But it is need to make students understand the historical background. Museums need to exhibit with various ideas.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="jpn">ほとんどの学校博物館には教室の復元がある。それは生徒たちが学校の歴史を理解する上で 有益である。しかし、そこに教師の姿は見られない。たとえば、ロッテルダムの国立学校博物館には 5つの教室がある。すなわち、1662年の村の学校、1830年のモデル学校、1910年の教室、1910年の教 室、1960年の教室である。しかし、1662年の村の学校に1人の教師がいるだけである。それは17世紀 オランダの有名な画家、アドリアン・ヴァン・オスターデの絵から再構成されたものである。この絵 はルーブル博物館で見ることができる。ドレスデンの学校博物館にも、ドイツ帝国時代、ワイマール 共和国時代、ドイツ民主共和国の時代など3つの教室が復元されているが、やはり教師の姿はない。 教師の姿は、学校博物館よりもむしろおもちゃ博物館に見られるが、それはミニチュア であり、男性教師に限られる。女性の教師はいない。学校博物館では教師集団も見られない。それ は、オランダ、ドイツ、スイス、チェコ、韓国そして日本でも同様である。 その理由は、歴史的・社会的条件の反映である。しかし、生徒に歴史的背景を理解させ る必要がある。博物館は、さまざまなアイディアで工夫をして展示することが必要である。</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Elke Urban (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37657">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37657</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37657</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37657">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <pre xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">There is the restoration of classroom at almost school museum. It is instructive for students to
understand the history of the school. But we cannot find the image of teacher there. For example there are 5
classrooms in the National School Museum in Rotterdam: the village school of 1662, the model school in 1830,
classroom of 1910, classroom of 1930, classroom of 1960. But there is only one teacher in the village school of
1662 and it is reconstructed from a painting by the famous 17th century Dutch painter Adriaen van Ostade. This
picture is able to be seen in the Louvre. There are 3 classrooms in the School Museum in Dresden: in the
German Empire (1871-1918), in the Weimar Republic(1919-1933) and in the German Democratic
Republic(1949-1990). But we cannot find the image of teacher also.
We can find the image of teacher at the toy museum rather than at the school museum. It is the
miniature and only male teacher. There are few women teachers. We cannot find the teachers’ gatherings also
at the school museum. I have visited to the school museum or toy museum in Holland, in England, in Germany,
in Austria, in Switzerland, in Czech, in Korea and in Japan, but it is the same conditions. It is difficult to
imagine the activity of teachers.
I think that the reason is the reflection of historical and social conditions. But it is need to make students
understand the historical background. Museums need to exhibit with various ideas.</pre>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/CXzq8MvxkrM"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37656"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37657" ADMID="premis.37657 entity.37657">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
