<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37709"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-31T12:03:15"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-16T10:59:09"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Meden, Katja</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37709" GROUPID="37709">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Teacher´s associations and institutions in Slovakia</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="slk">Učiteľské spolky a organizácie na Slovensku</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Michalička, Vladimír</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:creator>Vaněková, Daniela</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">Similar to the Craft Guilds - groups of tradesmen or craftsmen engaged in the same occupation joined together in the Middle ages, since the end of the 18th century associations and commissions of teachers can be traced. They were established in order to improve professional, cultural and social status of the teachers. In the history of education in Slovakia, the Association of teachers in the Malohont region (1786) and The Commission of Teachers from the Liptov region (1836) were the oldest. The first associations had an independent character related mostly to a particular region or church. After the issue of the Hungarian School Law in 1868, there was an increase in foundation of new associations which were formed according to the school types. After the establishment of the independent Czechoslovakia, this increase continued. However, with the arrival of the Communist regime in 1948 a discontinuity can be observed. All the existing associoations were cancelled and replaced by one central trade union (Trade Union of teachers and employees in educational and cultural sector, later renamed to Trade Union of Education and Science). At the upcoming conference, Museum of Education and Pedagogy in Bratislava would like to present the theme of associations of teachers. As a source we use newspapers (periodicals) issued by these associations in the 20th century. The aim of our paper is the classification of the periodicals, analysis of their content, characteristics of the authors and the museum documentation of this part of our collections.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="slk">Tak ako v stredoveku existovali združenia remeselníkov – stredoveké cechy, tak od konca 18. storočia vznikali na našom území združenia, spolky, organizácie učiteľov, ktorých cieľom bolo zabezpečiť ich oprávnené stavovské, profesionálne, kultúrne a sociálne potreby. Zo slovenskej edukačnej histórie identifikujeme ako najstaršie združenie učiteľov Malohontský učiteľský spolok (zal. 1786), Vychovávateľský zbor učiteľov škôl v Liptove (zal. 1836) a neskôr aj ďalšie. Tieto prvé učiteľské združenia mali charakter individuálny, viazali sa na príslušný región, prípadne na spoločné vierovyznanie. Po vydaní uhorského školského zákona v roku 1868 začali vznikať masovejšie ďalšie učiteľské združenia, predovšetkým podľa stupňa a typu škôl, po vzniku samostatnej Československej republiky v roku 1918 tento nárast pokračoval. Po nastúpení komunistického režimu v roku 1948 došlo k extrému, keď dovtedajšie spolky a organizácie boli zrušené a nahradené jednotnou odborovou organizáciou – Odborovým zväzom zamestnancov školstva a kultúry, neskôr školstva a vedy (OZZŠaK, OZZŠaV). Múzeum školstva a pedagogiky v Bratislave chce na tomto podujatí predstaviť časť uvedenej historickej problematiky, a to časopisy (periodiká), ktoré vznikali z iniciatívy učiteľských spolkov v uplynulom 20. storočí. Náš príspevok bude zameraný na ich klasifikáciu, charakteristiku obsahovej náplne, charakteristiku prispievateľov a múzejnú dokumentáciu tejto časti nášho múzejného fondu.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Ljiljana Stankov (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-28</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37709">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37709</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37709</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37709">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">Similar to the Craft Guilds - groups of tradesmen or
                                        craftsmen engaged in the same occupation joined together in
                                        the Middle ages, since the end of the 18th century
                                        associations and commissions of teachers can be traced. They
                                        were established in order to improve professional, cultural
                                        and social status of the teachers. In the history of
                                        education in Slovakia, the Association of teachers in the
                                        Malohont region (1786) and The Commission of Teachers from
                                        the Liptov region (1836) were the oldest. The first
                                        associations had an independent character related mostly to
                                        a particular region or church. After the issue of the
                                        Hungarian School Law in 1868, there was an increase in
                                        foundation of new associations which were formed according
                                        to the school types. After the establishment of the
                                        independent Czechoslovakia, this increase continued.
                                        However, with the arrival of the Communist regime in 1948 a
                                        discontinuity can be observed. All the existing
                                        associoations were cancelled and replaced by one central
                                        trade union (Trade Union of teachers and employees in
                                        educational and cultural sector, later renamed to Trade
                                        Union of Education and Science). At the upcoming conference,
                                        Museum of Education and Pedagogy in Bratislava would like to
                                        present the theme of associations of teachers. As a source
                                        we use newspapers (periodicals) issued by these associations
                                        in the 20th century. The aim of our paper is the
                                        classification of the periodicals, analysis of their
                                        content, characteristics of the authors and the museum
                                        documentation of this part of our collections.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/ogiftr3gB_4"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37707"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37709" ADMID="premis.37709 entity.37709">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
