<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37696"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-31T09:21:57"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-16T10:54:18"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37696" GROUPID="37696">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Slovenian Teachers in Australia - Link Between Two Homelands</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="slv">Slovenski učitelji v Avstraliji - vez med dvema domovinama</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Čebulj Sajko, Breda</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The beginnings of establishing Slovenian schools in Australia, especially among the Slovenian people in the state of New South Wales, are connected to the formation of the first Slovenian Societies and religious centers in the second half of the fifties of the twentieth century. It was the Slovenian priests who, after mass on Saturdays, began with teaching the Slovene language. In the next decade the creation of Saturday schools among the Slovenian societies arose out of this spontaneous teaching. The teaching was done by volunteers, who had already worked in education before emigrating from their home-country. Among them there was a special position held by Jože Čuješ and Mariza Ličan, who are both deceased today. Through their life stories the author of this paper illuminates the incredibly fruitful era of development in Slovenian education in Australia from the sixties until the end of the last century. These forty years are a time of a plenty of Saturday schools, which had a decisive influence towards maintaining the Slovene language among the members of the second-generation children of Slovenian origin. In the time of multicultural policy, that is from the midseventies onward, Slovene language became an optional matura examination subject in high schools. To ease the coordination activities of the Slovenian community in the field of education the Slovenian Schools Committee was established. It’s creation had a decisive impact towards the opening of a Slovene language lectureship on Macquarie University in Sydney. After Čuješ’s death in the mid-nineties and Ličan’s in 2002, the Slovenian complementary education gradually vanished. The Slovenian identity of the descendants of the first generations of Australian Slovenians is gaining new qualities, which are no longer based on the Slovene language, but on feelings of affiliation with the ethnic origin of their parents and grandparents.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="slv">Začetek ustanavljanja slovenskih šol v Avstraliji, še posebno med Slovenci v državi Novi Južni Wales, so povezani z nastankom prvih slovenskih društev in verskih središč v drugi polovici petdesetih let preteklega stoletja. Ravno slovenski duhovniki so ob sobotah po mašah prvi začeli s poučevanjem slovenskega jezika. Iz sprva spontanega poučevanja so v naslednjem desetletju pri vseh slovenskih organizacijah že imeli svoje slovenske sobotne šole. V njih so poučevali prostovoljci, ki so prosvetno delo opravljali že doma pred izselitvijo. Med njima sta posebno mesto imela danes že pokojna Jože Čuješ in Mariza Ličan. Skozi njune življenjske pripovedi avtorica prispevka osvetli izredno plodno obdobje razvoja slovenskega šolstva v Avstraliji vse od šestdesetih let pa do konca prejšnjega stoletja; to je čas številnih sobotnih šol, ki so odločilno pripomogle k ohranjanju slovenskega jezika med pripadniki druge generacije otrok slovenskega porekla; v času multikulturalne politike, tj. od sredine sedemdesetih let dalje, je slovenski jezik postal izbirni maturitetni predmet na srednjih šolah; zaradi lažjega usklajenega delovanja slovenske skupnosti na področju slovenskega šolstva je bil tedaj ustanovljen Slovenski šolski odbor, ki je odločilno vplival na ustanovitev lektorata za slovenski jezik na Macquarie University v Sydneyju. Po smrti Čuješa sredi devetdesetih let ter Ličanove leta 2002, je slovensko dopolnilno šolstvo postopoma zamrlo. Slovenska identiteta potomcev prvih generacij avstralskih Slovencev dobiva novo vsebino, ki čedalje bolj temelji na občutkih pripadnosti poreklu svojih staršev, starih staršev in ne več slovenskemu jeziku.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Uwe Krebs (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-28</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37696">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37696</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37696</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37696">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The beginnings of establishing Slovenian schools in
                                        Australia, especially among the Slovenian people in the
                                        state of New South Wales, are connected to the formation of
                                        the first Slovenian Societies and religious centers in the
                                        second half of the fifties of the twentieth century. It was
                                        the Slovenian priests who, after mass on Saturdays, began
                                        with teaching the Slovene language. In the next decade the
                                        creation of Saturday schools among the Slovenian societies
                                        arose out of this spontaneous teaching. The teaching was
                                        done by volunteers, who had already worked in education
                                        before emigrating from their home-country. Among them there
                                        was a special position held by Jože Čuješ and Mariza Ličan,
                                        who are both deceased today. Through their life stories the
                                        author of this paper illuminates the incredibly fruitful era
                                        of development in Slovenian education in Australia from the
                                        sixties until the end of the last century. These forty years
                                        are a time of a plenty of Saturday schools, which had a
                                        decisive influence towards maintaining the Slovene language
                                        among the members of the second-generation children of
                                        Slovenian origin. In the time of multicultural policy, that
                                        is from the midseventies onward, Slovene language became an
                                        optional matura examination subject in high schools. To ease
                                        the coordination activities of the Slovenian community in
                                        the field of education the Slovenian Schools Committee was
                                        established. It’s creation had a decisive impact towards the
                                        opening of a Slovene language lectureship on Macquarie
                                        University in Sydney. After Čuješ’s death in the
                                        mid-nineties and Ličan’s in 2002, the Slovenian
                                        complementary education gradually vanished. The Slovenian
                                        identity of the descendants of the first generations of
                                        Australian Slovenians is gaining new qualities, which are no
                                        longer based on the Slovene language, but on feelings of
                                        affiliation with the ethnic origin of their parents and
                                        grandparents.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/0JMWZV33E6Q"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37690"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37696" ADMID="premis.37696 entity.37696">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
