<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37665"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-29T09:09:21"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-05-29T09:14:52"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37665" GROUPID="37665">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">CoDiSV: a research project on Aosta Valley schoolchildren's writings</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="ita">CoDiSV: un progetto di ricerca sulle scritture bambine valdostane</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Marini, Cristina Elena Maria</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:creator>Sacchi, Fabio</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="ita">Il progetto di ricerca sulle scritture bambine ha avuto inizio nel 2003 presso l’Università della Valle d’Aosta con lo scopo di raccogliere testimonianze sulle scritture bambine sia in lingua italiana sia in lingua francese. Il CoDiSV è un archivio digitale contenente quaderni di alunni, diari, registri e altro materiale scolastico prodotto dagli alunni valdostani in un arco temporale che va dall’unificazione nazionale (1860) ai giorni nostri. Queste fonti, per lungo tempo considerate “minori” dalla storiografia, sono in realtà capaci di dare un significativo apporto alla ricerca non solo per quanto concerne la storia della scuola, la didattica e gli studi sociali, ma anche (specialmente nel contesto plurilingue che caratterizza questa regione italiana) per quello che attiene indagini di tipo storico linguistico, sociolinguistico e dialettologico. La pubblicazione di documenti rappresenta un obiettivo primario insieme alla diffusione di conoscenza nella comunità scientifica e all’interazione tra tutti i soggetti interessati sia da un punto di vista professionale sia per motivi personali. Ad oggi il sito (www.codisv.it) contiene più di 1000 documenti digitalizzati che possono essere consultati grazie ad un motore di ricerca interno. Dal 2011 ha preso avvio la pubblicazione di contributi linguistici e multidisciplinari realizzati a partire dallo studio dei materiali del corpus.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The research project on schoolchildren's writings began in 2003 at the University of Aosta Valley with the aim of collecting testimonies of children's writings in Italian and French language. The CoDiSV is a digital archive containing children’s exercise books, diaries and other school material produced by children in Aosta Valley in a period from the unification of Italy (1861) to the present. This source, usually considered a poor and "minor" one, is in fact capable to significantly contribute not only to school history, didactics and society studies, but also (and this specially in the multilingual context which characterizes this region of Italy) to historical-linguistic, sociolinguistic and dialectological inquiries. The publication of such documents pursues the primary objective of providing information to the scientific community and promoting interaction with the CoDiSV research group, via the dedicated website; but it also aims to involve all those who, for professional or personal interest, deal with research fields which extend from general education history to Aosta Valley regional history. At present the website (www.codisv.it) contains more than 1.000 digitalized documents, that can be browsed by a dedicated search engine. As far as research products are concerned, since 2011 a publishing series collects linguistic studies and multidisciplinary contributions based on the study of the corpus.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Mathias Rösch (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-27</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37665">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37665</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37665</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37665">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <pre xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The research project on schoolchildren's writings began in 2003 at the University of Aosta Valley with
the aim of collecting testimonies of children's writings in Italian and French language. The CoDiSV is a digital
archive containing children’s exercise books, diaries and other school material produced by children in Aosta
Valley in a period from the unification of Italy (1861) to the present. This source, usually considered a poor and
"minor" one, is in fact capable to significantly contribute not only to school history, didactics and society
studies, but also (and this specially in the multilingual context which characterizes this region of Italy) to
historical-linguistic, sociolinguistic and dialectological inquiries. The publication of such documents pursues the
primary objective of providing information to the scientific community and promoting interaction with the
CoDiSV research group, via the dedicated website; but it also aims to involve all those who, for professional or
personal interest, deal with research fields which extend from general education history to Aosta Valley regional
history. At present the website (www.codisv.it) contains more than 1.000 digitalized documents, that can be
browsed by a dedicated search engine. As far as research products are concerned, since 2011 a publishing series
collects linguistic studies and multidisciplinary contributions based on the study of the corpus.</pre>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/maWGyq8sv5E"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37663"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37665" ADMID="premis.37665 entity.37665">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
