<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37724"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-06-12T10:35:57"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-06-12T10:52:27"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37724" GROUPID="37724">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Almanac The Society of Professors of Slovakia (1928-33) and its role in improvement of teacher preparation</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="slk">Sborník Spolku profesorov Slovákov v rokoch 1928-33 a jeho úloha v skvalitňovaní učiteľského vzdelávania</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Racekova, Katarina</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The Society of Professors of Slovakia was a very important association of teachers in the first half of the 20th century (during the existence of the 1st Czechoslovak Republic). Through its almanac it helped in searching the national identity of Slovak teachers, especially secondary school teachers. Apart from reinforcing patriotism the Almanac of the Society of Professors of Slovakia made a significant contribution to raising the quality standards of teacher education by issuing various articles. The largest role in shaping the Almanac being a professional journal was played by its editors. The paper deals with the textual analysis of the Almanac of the Society of Professors of Slovakia in the period of 1928-33, during which it was published under the leadership of the editor-in-chief Pavol Florek. Based on the written communication of the editor with contributors the paper describes Pavol Florek´s efforts to improve the professional quality of the journal. In this regard a significant contribution was made by Jan Kvacala, a founder of modern Comeniology in Slovakia. The last part of the paper provides a selection of the correspondence between Pavol Florek and Jan Kvacala in the form of commented letters, preserved in the manuscripts owned by Jan Kvacala.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="slk">Spolok profesorov Slovákov bol dôležitým učiteľským spolkom prvej polovice 20. storočia (v období 1. ČSR). Prostredníctvom svojho zborníka pomáhal hľadať národnú identitu slovenských učiteľov, najmä stredoškolských profesorov. Okrem posilňovania vlastenectva Sborník Spolku profesorov Slovákov prispieval svojimi článkami i k skvalitňovaniu učiteľského vzdelávania. Najväčšiu zásluhu na kreovaní zborníka ako odborného stavovského periodika mali jeho redaktori. Príspevok sa zaoberá obsahovou analýzou Sborníka Spolku profesorov Slovákov v rokoch 1928-33, kedy vychádzal pod redakčným vedením Pavla Floreka. Na základe písomnej korešpondencie redaktora s prispievateľmi dokumentuje snahu Pavla Floreka o zlepšovanie odbornej úrovne zborníka. K nej výraznou mierou napomohol Ján Kvačala, zakladateľ modernej komeniológie na Slovensku. Posledná časť príspevku prináša výber zo vzájomnej korešpondencie Pavla Floreka a Jána Kvačalu v podobe komentovaných listov, zachovaných v rukopisnej pozostalosti Jána Kvačalu.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Marjetka Balkovec Debevec (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013-06-28</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">mul</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37724">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37724</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37724</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37724">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The Society of Professors of Slovakia was a very important
                                        association of teachers in the first half of the 20th
                                        century (during the existence of the 1st Czechoslovak
                                        Republic). Through its almanac it helped in searching the
                                        national identity of Slovak teachers, especially secondary
                                        school teachers. Apart from reinforcing patriotism the
                                        Almanac of the Society of Professors of Slovakia made a
                                        significant contribution to raising the quality standards of
                                        teacher education by issuing various articles. The largest
                                        role in shaping the Almanac being a professional journal was
                                        played by its editors. The paper deals with the textual
                                        analysis of the Almanac of the Society of Professors of
                                        Slovakia in the period of 1928-33, during which it was
                                        published under the leadership of the editor-in-chief Pavol
                                        Florek. Based on the written communication of the editor
                                        with contributors the paper describes Pavol Florek´s efforts
                                        to improve the professional quality of the journal. In this
                                        regard a significant contribution was made by Jan Kvacala, a
                                        founder of modern Comeniology in Slovakia. The last part of
                                        the paper provides a selection of the correspondence between
                                        Pavol Florek and Jan Kvacala in the form of commented
                                        letters, preserved in the manuscripts owned by Jan
                                        Kvacala.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/jR9noxVhvT4"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37713"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37724" ADMID="premis.37724 entity.37724">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
