<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37368"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-03-29T22:56:28"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-04-07T11:15:29"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.4" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name>Mirc</METS:name>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37368" GROUPID="37368">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">The Grotesque Discussion About the Destiny of Slovenian Gymnasium of Gorizia, 1919-1922. How to Expel Slovenian Culture From the Cities.</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:creator>Dessardo, Andrea</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">For the real first time in its history, after World War I, Italy faced the problem how to treat linguistic minorites within its borders. Between the end of the war and the beginning of the Fascist era, the thought about minorities' rights was contradictory and vague. While the official attitude was to be respectful and democratic, in facts Italy gradually limited the public space of its non-Italian new citizens. The case of the Slovenian Gymnasium of Gorizia could be a specimen. The authorities officially claimed the right to mantain non-Italian schools, but only in areas where the minorities traditionally lived. From 1908 existed in Gorizia a Slovenian Gymnasium, never tolerated by Italian nationalists. After World War I it was closed and then temporally re-opened in the same building of the Slovenian Realschule in Idrija. The issue was to set Slovenian schools only in pure Slovenian towns, in which there were no Italians: since all the bigger towns in the Julian March had Italian majorities (Trieste, Gorizia, Capodistria…), Slovenian schools should be set only in small and marginal towns like Idrija and Tolmin. From 1919 to 1921 Italian politicians and intellectuals discussed in private letters and in the newspapers about where to transfer the Slovenian Gymnasium: to Ajdovščina, to Postojna or to Sežana, even to Vipava… But somebody also suggested to set it in pure Italian areas, far from the influence of potential Slovenian irredentism, like Udine or Cividale. The beginning of Fascist era finally decided the definitive closure of all non-Italian schools.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">medvojno obdobje</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">gimnazija</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">Gorica</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">Julijska krajina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">nacionalizem</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">interwar period</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">gymnasium</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">Gorizia</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">Julian March</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">nationalism</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2016-09-28</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37368">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37368</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37368</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37368">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng"> For the real first time
                                    in its history, after World War I, Italy faced the problem how
                                    to treat linguistic minorites within its borders. Between the
                                    end of the war and the beginning of the Fascist era, the thought
                                    about minorities' rights was contradictory and vague. While the
                                    official attitude was to be respectful and democratic, in facts
                                    Italy gradually limited the public space of its non-Italian new
                                    citizens. The case of the Slovenian Gymnasium of Gorizia could
                                    be a specimen. The authorities officially claimed the right to
                                    mantain non-Italian schools, but only in areas where the
                                    minorities traditionally lived. From 1908 existed in Gorizia a
                                    Slovenian Gymnasium, never tolerated by Italian nationalists.
                                    After World War I it was closed and then temporally re-opened in
                                    the same building of the Slovenian Realschule in Idrija. The
                                    issue was to set Slovenian schools only in pure Slovenian towns,
                                    in which there were no Italians: since all the bigger towns in
                                    the Julian March had Italian majorities (Trieste, Gorizia,
                                    Capodistria…), Slovenian schools should be set only in small and
                                    marginal towns like Idrija and Tolmin. From 1919 to 1921 Italian
                                    politicians and intellectuals discussed in private letters and
                                    in the newspapers about where to transfer the Slovenian
                                    Gymnasium: to Ajdovščina, to Postojna or to Sežana, even to
                                    Vipava… But somebody also suggested to set it in pure Italian
                                    areas, far from the influence of potential Slovenian
                                    irredentism, like Udine or Cividale. The beginning of Fascist
                                    era finally decided the definitive closure of all non-Italian
                                    schools. </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qyvAj-oXzdM"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37356"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37368" ADMID="premis.37368 entity.37368">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
