<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/14269"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2012-11-30T11:46:54"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-02-09T10:37:13"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.14269" GROUPID="14269">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="slv">Represija, zločini i nezakonitosti vojnih i civilnih organa vlasti u hrvatskom dijelu Istre 1945.–1950.</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="eng">Repression, Crimes and Wrongful Acts of the Military and Civilian Authorities in the Croatian Part of Istria 1945–1950</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Dukovski, Darko</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="eng">In the five-year post-war period Istria went through processes of state-legaltransition, that is, through the processes of unifi cation with Croatia and Slovenia within Yugoslavia. During this very sensitive period, in the circumstancesof the division of its territory, uncertainty, socio-political transformation, and formation of the new government, numerous wrongful acts, instances of repression and crimes against anyone attempting to slow down or put a stop to these processes took place. The goal of the main political processes was to establish and strengthen the new people’s authorities under the supervision of the Military Administration of the Yugoslav Army in the transitional period of Istria’s unification with Yugoslavia or Slovenia and Croatia. During this time the foreign-political tensions and national-ideological division of the people were quite evident. In the short post-war period the people’s authorities were not completely communist, eventhough they acted under the supervision of the Party structures. The Party’s controlhad not yet been completely established. In this sense the repression against political opposition was also not exclusively communist. Certainly in the area controlled by the Military Administration of the Yugoslav Army the revolutionary social changes were introduced immediately, very often encountering the resistance of the population – Italian as well as Croatian and Slovenian. Thus the repression was aimed against the former wartime enemies, war criminals, collaborators, fascists, ideological-political and national enemies, recentallies and comrades in arms – all those who would in any way whatsoever hinder or interfere with the implementation of the political directives of the Party.</dcterms:abstract>
            <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="hrv">Istra je u petogodišnjem poratnom razdoblju prolazila kroz procese državno-pravne tranzicije, odnosno procese sjedinjenja s Hrvatskom i Slovenijom u Jugoslaviji. Tijekom toga, vrlo osjetljivoga razdoblja, podvojenosti njezina teritorija, neizvjesnosti i društveno-političke preobrazbe, izrastanja nove vlasti, događale su se brojne nezakonitosti, represije i zločini nad svima koji su te procese pokušali usporiti ili zaustaviti. Glavni politički procesi usmjereni su k uspostavi i učvršćenju nove narodne vlasti pod nadzorom Vojne uprave Jugoslavenske armije u prijelaznom razdoblju sjedinjenja Istre s Jugoslavijom, odnosno Slovenijom i Hrvatskom. ukojemu su se snažno osjećale vanjskopolitičke tenzije i nacionalno-ideološka podijeljenost stanovništva. Narodna vlast u kratkom poratnom razdoblju nije ucijelosti bila komunistička i ako je djelovala pod nadzorom partijskih struktura. Kontrola Partije nije bila tada do kraja uspostavljena. U tom smislu ni represijanad političkom oporbom nije nosila isključivo komunistički pečat. Nedvojbenoje da se na području kontroliranom od VUJA-e odmah počelo s provođenjem revolucionarnih društvenih promjena koje su vrlo često nailazile na otpor stanovništva, kako italijanskog tako i hrvatskog i slovenskog. Represija je bila usmjerena prema bivšem ratnom neprijatelju, ratnim zločincima, kolaboracionistima, fašistima, ideološko-političkim i nacionalnom neprijatelju, dojučerašnjim saveznicima i suborcima, svima onima koji su na bilo kojinačin sprječavali ili ometali provođenje političkih smjernica Partije.</dcterms:abstract>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino/Institute of Contemporary History, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2012-11-07</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">hrv</dcterms:language>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.14269">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>14269</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/14269</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.14269">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="slv">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">Istra je u petogodišnjem poratnom razdoblju prolazila kroz
                                        procese državno-pravne tranzicije, odnosno procese
                                        sjedinjenja s Hrvatskom i Slovenijom u Jugoslaviji. Tijekom
                                        toga, vrlo osjetljivoga razdoblja, podvojenosti njezina
                                        teritorija, neizvjesnosti i društveno-političke preobrazbe,
                                        izrastanja nove vlasti, događale su se brojne nezakonitosti,
                                        represije i zločini nad svima koji su te procese pokušali
                                        usporiti ili zaustaviti. Glavni politički procesi usmjereni
                                        su k uspostavi i učvršćenju nove narodne vlasti pod nadzorom
                                        Vojne uprave Jugoslavenske armije u prijelaznom razdoblju
                                        sjedinjenja Istre s Jugoslavijom, odnosno Slovenijom i
                                        Hrvatskom. ukojemu su se snažno osjećale vanjskopolitičke
                                        tenzije i nacionalno-ideološka podijeljenost stanovništva.
                                        Narodna vlast u kratkom poratnom razdoblju nije ucijelosti
                                        bila komunistička i ako je djelovala pod nadzorom partijskih
                                        struktura. Kontrola Partije nije bila tada do kraja
                                        uspostavljena. U tom smislu ni represijanad političkom
                                        oporbom nije nosila isključivo komunistički pečat.
                                        Nedvojbenoje da se na području kontroliranom od VUJA-e odmah
                                        počelo s provođenjem revolucionarnih društvenih promjena
                                        koje su vrlo često nailazile na otpor stanovništva, kako
                                        italijanskog tako i hrvatskog i slovenskog. Represija je
                                        bila usmjerena prema bivšem ratnom neprijatelju, ratnim
                                        zločincima, kolaboracionistima, fašistima,
                                        ideološko-političkim i nacionalnom neprijatelju,
                                        dojučerašnjim saveznicima i suborcima, svima onima koji su
                                        na bilo kojinačin sprječavali ili ometali provođenje
                                        političkih smjernica Partije.</p>
               </entity:description>
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <p xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">In the five-year post-war period Istria went through
                                        processes of state-legaltransition, that is, through the
                                        processes of unifi cation with Croatia and Slovenia within
                                        Yugoslavia. During this very sensitive period, in the
                                        circumstancesof the division of its territory, uncertainty,
                                        socio-political transformation, and formation of the new
                                        government, numerous wrongful acts, instances of repression
                                        and crimes against anyone attempting to slow down or put a
                                        stop to these processes took place. The goal of the main
                                        political processes was to establish and strengthen the new
                                        people’s authorities under the supervision of the Military
                                        Administration of the Yugoslav Army in the transitional
                                        period of Istria’s unification with Yugoslavia or Slovenia
                                        and Croatia. During this time the foreign-political tensions
                                        and national-ideological division of the people were quite
                                        evident. In the short post-war period the people’s
                                        authorities were not completely communist, eventhough they
                                        acted under the supervision of the Party structures. The
                                        Party’s controlhad not yet been completely established. In
                                        this sense the repression against political opposition was
                                        also not exclusively communist. Certainly in the area
                                        controlled by the Military Administration of the Yugoslav
                                        Army the revolutionary social changes were introduced
                                        immediately, very often encountering the resistance of the
                                        population – Italian as well as Croatian and Slovenian. Thus
                                        the repression was aimed against the former wartime enemies,
                                        war criminals, collaborators, fascists,
                                        ideological-political and national enemies, recentallies and
                                        comrades in arms – all those who would in any way whatsoever
                                        hinder or interfere with the implementation of the political
                                        directives of the Party.</p>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/embed/h7zmahBUKzg"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/14256"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.14269" ADMID="premis.14269 entity.14269">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
