<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<METS:mets xmlns:METS="http://www.loc.gov/METS/"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:dcmitype="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/"
           xmlns:premis="http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:entity="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity"
           TYPE="entity"
           OBJID="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37658"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/METS/ http://www.loc.gov/mets/mets.xsd http://purl.org/dc/terms/ http://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/dcterms.xsd http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-0.xsd http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1 http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/v1/PREMIS-v1-1.xsd">
   <METS:metsHdr CREATEDATE="2017-05-25T11:55:01"
                 LASTMODDATE="2017-05-25T11:58:05"
                 RECORDSTATUS="Active">
      <METS:agent ROLE="DISSEMINATOR" TYPE="ORGANIZATION">
         <METS:name>SIstory</METS:name>
         <METS:note>http://sistory.si/</METS:note>
      </METS:agent>
      <METS:agent ROLE="CREATOR" ID="user.100" TYPE="INDIVIDUAL">
         <METS:name/>
      </METS:agent>
   </METS:metsHdr>
   <METS:dmdSec ID="dc.37658" GROUPID="37658">
      <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
         <METS:xmlData>
            <dcterms:title xml:lang="eng">Teacher's Associations in the Collection of Photographs of the Croatian School Museum</dcterms:title>
            <dcterms:alternative xml:lang="hrv">Učiteljske udruge u Zbirci fotografija Hrvatskoga školskog muzeja</dcterms:alternative>
            <dcterms:creator>Serdar, Elizabeta</dcterms:creator>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="eng">The Collection of Photographs of the Croatian School Museum documents the establishment and activities of the most significant teachers' associations in Croatia. Some of the oldest photographs included in the collection are related to the establishment, i.e. opening of the Museum in 1901. In addition to the preserved photographs, the collection also presents traces of the past of the Museum through related literature, i.e. the Museum's first inventory records. Keeping pace with other European countries, Croatia followed the achievements in the field of photography and development of photographic techniques in the 19th century. That was the time when the first traveling photographers appeared and permanent photographic ateliers were established in Zagreb and other Croatian towns, such as Karlovac, Petrinja, Varaždin, etc. (Pommer, Standl, Varga, etc.). The most important events and most significant people from different walks of social life were photographed for documentary purposes. This is how the first photographs related to education and the first teachers' associations were created, collected and stored. The Croatian School Museum thus stores photographs presenting the members of one of the first Croatian teachers' associations, Teacher's Cooperative (Učiteljska zadruga), established in 1865, and the founders of the Croatian Pedagogical Literary Society (Hrvatski pedagoško-književni zbor) established in 1871, who also established the Croatian School Museum. Furthermore, the photographs serve as documentary evidence about the establishment of teacher associations across Croatia, as well as various teacher assemblies and training programs organized in the country and abroad in connection with teacher associations. It is mainly through their activities within their associations that teachers, especially in the 19th century, promoted the advanced pedagogical ideas and influenced the development of education and pedagogy.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:description xml:lang="hrv">Zbirka fotografija Hrvatskoga školskog muzeja dokumentira nastanak i djelovanje najznačajnijih učiteljskih udruga u Hrvatskoj. Počeci sakupljanja fotografske građe vezani su uz sami osnutak, odnosno otvaranje Muzeja 1901.g. Pored samih sačuvanih fotografija u zbirci, tragove o tome nalazimo i u popratnoj dokumentaciji - prvim inventarnim knjigama koje muzej posjeduje. Ne zaostajući za drugim europskim zemljama, Hrvatska prati otkrića na području fotografije i razvitak fotografskih tehnika u 19. stoljeću. Javljaju se prvi putujući fotografi, ali i stalni fotografski atelijeri u Zagrebu i drugim hrvatskim gradovima – Karlovcu, Petrinji, Varaždinu... (Pommer, Standl, Varga...). Fotografski se bilježe najvažnija događanja te fotografiraju najznačajne osobe iz različitih područja društvenog života. Tako nastaju, prikupljaju se i čuvaju i prve fotografije vezane uz školstvo, a ujedno i uz prva udruživanja učitelja. U Hrvatskome školskom muzeju tako su sačuvane fotografije koje prikazuju članove jedne od prvih hrvatskih učiteljskih udruga - Učiteljsku zadrugu osnovanu 1865., a također i osnivače Hrvatskoga pedagogijsko-književnoga zbora (ujedno i osnivače našega muzeja) iz 1871. g. Nadalje, fotografije svjedoče o udruživanju učitelja diljem Hrvatske, održavanju različitih učiteljskih skupština i tečajeva u zemlji i inozemstvu, vezanih uz njihovo udruživanje. Upravo kroz rad u svojim udrugama, učitelji, naročito u 19. stoljeću, najčešće promoviraju napredne pedagoške ideje i utječu na razvitak školstva i pedagogije.</dcterms:description>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">zgodovina</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">šolstvo</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="slv">muzej</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">history</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">school system</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:subject xml:lang="eng">museum</dcterms:subject>
            <dcterms:publisher>Slovenski šolski muzej, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>ICOM Slovenija, Celje</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:publisher>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Ljubljana</dcterms:publisher>
            <dcterms:contributor>Elke Urban (moderator)</dcterms:contributor>
            <dcterms:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">2013</dcterms:date>
            <dcterms:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage</dcterms:type>
            <dcterms:language xsi:type="dcterms:ISO639-3">eng</dcterms:language>
            <dcterms:license xsi:type="dcterms:URI">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/si/</dcterms:license>
            <dcterms:license xml:lang="slv">Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialo-Brez predelav 2.5 Slovenija (CC BY-NC-ND 2.5 SI)</dcterms:license>
         </METS:xmlData>
      </METS:mdWrap>
   </METS:dmdSec>
   <METS:amdSec ID="entity">
      <METS:techMD ID="premis.37658">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="PREMIS:OBJECT" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData>
               <premis:object>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>SIstory Entity ID</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>37658</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectIdentifier>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierType>hdl</premis:objectIdentifierType>
                     <premis:objectIdentifierValue>http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37658</premis:objectIdentifierValue>
                  </premis:objectIdentifier>
                  <premis:objectCategory>Entity</premis:objectCategory>
               </premis:object>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
      <METS:techMD ID="entity.37658">
         <METS:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="ENTITY" MIMETYPE="text/xml">
            <METS:xmlData xsi:schemaLocation="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity ../../v3/entity.1.0.xsd">
               <entity:description xml:lang="eng">
                  <pre xmlns="http://sistory.si/schema/sistory/v3/entity">The Collection of Photographs of the Croatian School Museum documents the establishment and
activities of the most significant teachers' associations in Croatia. Some of the oldest photographs included in
the collection are related to the establishment, i.e. opening of the Museum in 1901. In addition to the preserved
photographs, the collection also presents traces of the past of the Museum through related literature, i.e. the
Museum's first inventory records.
Keeping pace with other European countries, Croatia followed the achievements in the field of
photography and development of photographic techniques in the 19th century. That was the time when the first
traveling photographers appeared and permanent photographic ateliers were established in Zagreb and other
Croatian towns, such as Karlovac, Petrinja, Varaždin, etc. (Pommer, Standl, Varga, etc.). The most important
events and most significant people from different walks of social life were photographed for documentary
purposes. This is how the first photographs related to education and the first teachers' associations were created,
collected and stored.
The Croatian School Museum thus stores photographs presenting the members of one of the first
Croatian teachers' associations, Teacher's Cooperative (Učiteljska zadruga), established in 1865, and the
founders of the Croatian Pedagogical Literary Society (Hrvatski pedagoško-književni zbor) established in 1871,
who also established the Croatian School Museum. Furthermore, the photographs serve as documentary
evidence about the establishment of teacher associations across Croatia, as well as various teacher assemblies
and training programs organized in the country and abroad in connection with teacher associations. It is mainly
through their activities within their associations that teachers, especially in the 19th century, promoted the
advanced pedagogical ideas and influenced the development of education and pedagogy.</pre>
               </entity:description>
            </METS:xmlData>
         </METS:mdWrap>
      </METS:techMD>
   </METS:amdSec>
   <METS:fileSec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      <METS:fileGrp USE="DEFAULT">
         <METS:file ID="video1" USE="EXTERNAL">
            <METS:FLocat USE="YOUTUBE"
                         LOCTYPE="URL"
                         xlink:href="//www.youtube.com/embed/a5-UdpGUGes"/>
         </METS:file>
      </METS:fileGrp>
   </METS:fileSec>
   <METS:structMap xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   LABEL="SIstory"
                   TYPE="dependent">
      <METS:div TYPE="entity">
         <METS:mptr LOCTYPE="HANDLE" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/37656"/>
         <METS:div TYPE="entity" DMDID="dc.37658" ADMID="premis.37658 entity.37658">
            <METS:fptr FILEID="video1"/>
         </METS:div>
      </METS:div>
   </METS:structMap>
</METS:mets>
